<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sampsons iavvbone against the spiritual Philistine Containing sundry godly and Christian praiers, necessarie and conuenient for all estates and occasions: by Ed. Hutchins.</title>
            <author>Hutchins, Edward, 1558?-1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 144 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14118</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840052</idno>
  <idno type="VID">176864</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248569110</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 14014</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S104314</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99840052e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14118)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176864)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 715:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sampsons iavvbone against the spiritual Philistine Containing sundry godly and Christian praiers, necessarie and conuenient for all estates and occasions: by Ed. Hutchins.</title>
                  <author>Hutchins, Edward, 1558?-1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[18], 159 [i.e. 259], [11] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Peter Short,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>"A briefe narration of Dauids case" has separate divisional title; pagination and register are continuous.</note>
                  <note>With four final contents leaves and a colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>P. 259 misnumbered 159.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">David, --  King of Israel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Prayers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176864:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176864:1"/>
                  <p>SAMPSONS IAVVBONE a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Spiritual Philistine.</p>
                  <p>Containing sundry <hi>Godly and Christian prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> necessarie and conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for all estates and occasions: by <hi>Ed. Hutchins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>1. <hi>Peter,</hi> 4.7.</bibl> Now, The end of all things is at hand: be yee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore sober and watch in praier.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Printed by</hi> Peter Short. 1601.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                     <p>H D</p>
                     <figDesc>decorative border incorporating the Royal Arms and printer's device of Peter Short</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176864:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176864:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>To the Honourable</hi> and his approued <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and Aunt, the Lady</hi> Iane Wentwoorth, Edward <hi>Hut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chins wisheth all happinesse in Christ Iesus.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough manie yeers since, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Oxford but a young Student, I tooke some pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate paines in the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of <hi>Dauids Sling;</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:176864:3"/>since that time haue had small leisure to attende a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further trauell in such respect: yet to shewe my thankefull minde of your Honourable fauoures to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes me, I haue striuen by stealth of houres to draw this shorte prayer booke, beseeching your accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof.</p>
                  <p>I haue therein deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that matter, which I trust is sound and necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for particular person, and case: And pray God, it maie redounde to the profit of the Reader, as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion
<pb facs="tcp:176864:3"/>serueth. Thus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of your Honors coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, I offer it as some pledge of my bounden re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, and so com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you and all your cares to the Almighty. The sixt of Aprill, Anno 1601.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your H. to commaund,</hi> EDVV. HVTCHINS one of the Prebenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of new Sarum.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176864:4"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:176864:4"/>
                  <head>To the Christian Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>grace and peace, from</hi> God our Father by the merits of <hi>our alone Sauiour Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus,</hi> be multiplied.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Christian exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise of sacred and sanctifying praier (christian Reader) is of that excellencie, necessitie, and efficacy, as that it neither nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, nor is possible worthily to be expressed or commended by the tongue or pen of man. For if we consider first the Author thereof who is the holy Lorde of heauen and earth, infinite in power, wisedome and mercie, we must needes confesse he would not haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and so often enioined
<pb facs="tcp:176864:5"/>his seruants to the zealous and constant practise of this princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall and most powrefull duetie, had not he who is onely wise, nay rather who is wisedome and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes it selfe, seene it to haue been most necessarie and profitable for them. 2. The manifold and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall precepts &amp; exhortations of the Prophets, Apostles, our bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Sauiour Christ Iesus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and his faithfull Ministers from time to time, to admonish and incite vs to the practise here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Thirdlie if we consider the constant and continuall practise of all the fathfull Patriarches, Prophets, and Apostles, yea moreouer of the ordinary and continuall vse hereof by our most holy, immaculate, and most glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb facs="tcp:176864:5"/>Sauiour and of that innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable cloude of witnesses of Saints, Martyrs, and all others the faithfull seruantes of God: as <hi>Abraham</hi> and his posteritie, <hi>Moyses, Ioshua, Sampson Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon, Elias Daniel,</hi> and all the rest of the Prophetes and holie men of God, did vs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>llie in all their distresses striue with God, as <hi>Iacob</hi> did wrastle with the Angell. Fourthlie the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sities &amp; occasions that daily and hourelie euen force and compell all the Lordes deere Children to the constant and faithfull pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise hereof: for whether we looke vnto the benefites of Almightie God past, present, or to come, which euerie houre and minute of our life we haue, doe, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb facs="tcp:176864:6"/>to enioie which are innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; or to the dangers, mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, afflictions, or iudgementes haue befallen vs, hang ouer our heades, or maie euerie minute seaze vpon vs, we are called, yea forciblie summoned to this holie and most necessarie duetie. Fiftlie if we regard the most gracious and mercifull promises, freelie made vnto vs to allure vs hereto, and that for our owne good. Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the heauie iudgements threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and executed vpon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and carelesse neglectors of this duetie. And lastlie the continnall dailie lip-labour and fruitles and ignorant, yea sinfull blasphemous mumbling of the sottishe Idolatrous Papistes, whose constant practise in this
<pb facs="tcp:176864:6"/>case shall rise vp in iudgement against manie millions of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, that make no conscience to consecrate some daylie opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities or howers for this spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall duetie. These Motiues (good Reader) with infinit moe which I can not remember vnto thee, ought to spurre thee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the constant and conscio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable practise of this exercise of holie and feruent prayer, and for thy helpe and furtheraunce herein, the gracious, wise, and mercifull prouidence of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie Father hath raised vppe manie of his faithfull seruants and Ministers, to set downe and publishe sundrie and diuers fourmes of godlie and Christian Prayers, for thy furtheraunce
<pb facs="tcp:176864:7"/>and direction at all times, and vpon all occasions. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, least thou shouldest be glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and so begin to loathe this most wholesome and necessarie spirituall foode of thy soule, the Spirit of God hath disposed so, that diuers of the said treatises of prayer do carie most amiable and delightfull countenances as it were outwardlie, the rather to affect and winne thee to the loue and embracing of at least some of them. As if thy heart be set vpon treasure, there is one ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that title of, <hi>The treasure of gladnes;</hi> an other <hi>The Pathway to saluation,</hi> an other <hi>The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Garden,</hi> also <hi>The enimie to securitie,</hi> and one amongst the rest beares this title, <hi>Dauids
<pb facs="tcp:176864:7"/>Sling,</hi> which godlie and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Treatise was manie yeares ago published by this Author, to the great comfort and benefit of many thousand the seruants of God. These goodly titles no doubt were put vppon these treatises purposelie, the rather to affect and delight the Readers with the loue of this exercise, euen as the discreet &amp; carefull Phisition doth often deale with his weake and ill affectionated stomacke and eie of his patient, who when his stomacke hath bin cloied with ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king many medicines and his tast offended with the bitternesse of them, his eie also begins to abhor the sight and colour thereof: I say then the Physition doth many times couer his med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:176864:8"/>pill, cordiall preseruatiue, or restoratiue with fine gold, that both the eie may the rather be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted therewith, and the pallate kept from the taste thereof, and so the pattent entised to receiue the same for his owne good. Now if all these and verie manie other meanes haue bin deuised, to draw thee to the loue and liking of this most necessarie and christian du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and that for thine eternall good and saluation, what remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth but that thou at length con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre with thy owne soule of these things diligently and faithfullie, and if thou hast been carelesse and negligent herein, repent and call earnestly to the Lord to renew re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, direct, and assist thee: If thou haue made some conscience
<pb facs="tcp:176864:8"/>of the daily and conscionable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise of this dutie, proceed &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, knowing that he that put<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth his hand to the plough and looketh backe is not meete for the kingdom of heauē; and that only he which endureth to the end shal be saued. Thou seest how watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and malicious Sathan is now his kingdom is almost at an end, to stir vp millions of his instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mēts &amp; ministers in these dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous daies of ours, as many cursed Atheists &amp; abhominable Papists, with sundry other damnable He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, and false and carnal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, to extinguish the blessed light of the glorious Gospell of Christ Iesus, and the most woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and sacred instrument there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, euen our gratious and dread
<pb facs="tcp:176864:9"/>soueraigne, the blessed and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable light, of this Israell of God. It standeth vs therefore in hand to be sober and to be watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto praier, and to looke to our lampes and to our oyle, that at what houre of the day or night the Lord shall call for vs, we may bee found in the knowledge and true faith of the Lord Iesus, and in the obedience and practise of his commandements; that so we maie enter with him into that happie and glorious rest, prepared for all the adopted children of our heauenly father: which he grant vs for his Christ sake, Amen.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Farewell in Christ.</salute>
                     <signed>E. H.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="prayers">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:176864:9"/>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A CONFESSION OF SINNE.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Ought (O Lorde) to take heed to my waies, that I sinne not against thee: but, alas, I am fraile and readie to hault: I ought to follow goodnesse, but I follow euill for good; nay, alasse, mine iniquities are gone ouer mine head, and as a weighty burthen, they are too heauie for mee. O Lord in this case what shal I do? I haue no comfort in my selfe, but on thee will I waite; my heartshall pant after thy sweete
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:176864:10"/>comforts, rebuke mee not in thine anger; &amp; if thine arrowes light vppon me for my sinnes, yet (O Lord) remember me in thy mercie, make me sorie for my foolishnesse, that I may taste of thy sweetenesse: and to the end I may bridle my selfe, and runne my race in thy waies, giue me grace to thinke vppon mine ende, and the measure of my daies, how small it is, and howe there remaineth after death a iudgement: that so li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in thy feare, I may liue by thy loue, partaker of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and free from damnation, thorough Iesus Christ my deere redeemer, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:176864:10"/>
                     <head>A prayer for remission of sinne.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord GOD, thou art a louer of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnes, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of iniquity; and I miserable creature, haue hated righteousnes, and loued iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: and therefore (O God) if thou shouldest marke what I haue doone amisse, I were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer able to abide it; if thou wouldest dispute with Iob, hee were not able to answere thee one for a thousande; and what am I to a Iob? O Lorde, therefore where thou knowest my follies, how I am laden with sinne, giue me grace to be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:176864:11"/>with the burthen thereof, that I may come to thee, and finde ease by thee; let me not feare, but be of good cheere in thee; strengthen me with thy spirite, send him to be my comforter, to crie it in my heart, that thou art my louing Father, that I may neuer despaire of thy fauour; assuring my selfe, that thy grace is sufficient for mee, euen as mighty as thy selfe. Remember (O Lord) the prodigall Sonnes repenting, and vppon repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance the ioy of his Father in forgiuing, and finding his sonne that was lost; O Lord, be thou the like father to me, to giue me shooe and ring; thy fat calfe is killed, O let me feed vpon him, and tast of his sweetnes, Purge
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:176864:11"/>me (O Father) in the bloud of thy Sonne; loue me in him thy beloued, that I may liue by thy loue. Sinne deserueth a curse; but in Christ made a curse, free me from thy curse: forgiue, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all my sins. Graunt this (O Father) for his sake, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no sin, became sin for my sake, to saue me from sinne, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for mortification.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>In, O God, is only and properly euill, that made of a good Angell a diuell, who watcheth like a Serpent craftily, and like a Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mightily to snare vs in sinne:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:176864:12"/>O Lorde, therefore giue mee grace to eschew sin, to represse euill, that I may escape the fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie darts of the diuell. My duetie is to keepe sin from raigning, to destroy the bodie of sin, to cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the flesh with the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and lusts thereof; this is the charge which thou hast cast vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me and all Christians: but (al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s) wretches that we are, of our selues, we are so farre from thy will, that euery man is of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe a very satan, enimy to god, and therfore to all that good is: O Lord, therfore able me to do thy will, giue mee grace to doe what thou commandest, and then command what thou plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest, that I may please thee, and for euer praise thee for thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:176864:12"/>Graunt this I beseech thee most merciful father, for Iesus Christes sake, my onely sauiour and redeemer, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for amendment of life.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Mercifull God, where thy will is, our sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, I beseech thee pardon all my sins, to create a new hart, and to renew my spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within me; strengthen mee (O Lord) to deny my selfe, to follow thee in wisedome, like a Serpent; in simplicity, like a Doue; in humility, like a lambe; O giue mee grace in all my pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage to make thee my way,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:176864:13"/>against the father of lies; to cleaue to thee for my trueth, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all the works of darknes; to follow thee for my light, that my faith may be seene by good works. Let me not (O Lord) be like the figgetree, greene with leaues: for bare saying is not the way to be saued: figs, O Lord, do please thee, and without figs the figtree is cursed. O Lord, it is a hell to haue thy <hi>(nescio:)</hi> giue mee grace to bee wise, to watch for thy comming, with Lampe and Oile, that I maie haue thy <hi>(scio)</hi> to be knowne of thee, that I may knowe, and knowing may followe thee in heauen for euer: giue me grace to haue peace with all men, as much as is possible, that I may
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:176864:13"/>bee blessed with the peacema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker: to be lowly and meeke, that I may be blessed with the poore in spirit; to hunger and thirst af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thy Kingdome; to heare thy voice, and to follow the same; that I may neuer perish. And now (O Lorde) I instantly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee, the rather to guide me in the waies of thy will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the world is like a Sodom, and it is a speciall grace to bee a Lot in Sodome. Noe was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in his generation, the daies of Noe are come vpon vs; giue me grace to bee perfect, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low S. Anne in fasting and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, father Simeon in piety and dnuotion, S. Mary in humilitie and obedience, our Sauiour in charity and godly life: giue me
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:176864:14"/>grace to keepe my selfe purely religious, to visite fatherles and Widowes, to feede thee in thy hungring, to refresh thee in thy thirsting, to cloath thee in thy naked, to comfort thee in thy comfortles seruants, and to keep my selfe vnspotted of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent euill worlde, which lieth wholy in wickednes; that so I may be found one of thy sheep, to be placed at thy right hand, to heare from thy mouth the blessed sentence, that I am the blessed of thy Father, to possesse heauen thy kingdome prepared for all the elect. Grant this (O Father) for Iesus Christes sake, our only mediator and Redeemer, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:176864:14"/>
                     <head>A complaint, with a prayer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst sinne.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, this is that late and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable daye of the world, wherein the diuels flood increaseth, and thy drop is very little: the world is full of sin, and so full of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that Iacob cannot es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape from halting, wrestle hee neuer so well: O God, therfore be thou my deare father; I pray thee therefore preserue me from euill. I haue hearde of thy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty mercy, whereby thou couldest and diddest keepe thy secrete ones to thy selfe in the middest of a wicked and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerse
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:176864:15"/>generation: Tread of Iob in the land of Hus; of Lot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Sodomites; of the Bishoppe of Pergamus, euen where the seate of Satan was: O Lorde, shewe the might of thy grace towards mee, so far as to keepe me within thy Arke. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are the Goates, let mee bee one of thy Lambes and little flocke; giue mee thy Spirite to assist and guide me to walke in thy waie, the onely trueth and life, in Iesus Christ thy one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Sonne; let him be mine ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to followe, let his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise encourage mee, let him be my reward, that I may liue with thee for euer, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:176864:15"/>
                     <head>A comfortable Meditation in time of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, nothing greeueth the godly so much, as to seem to bee forsaken of thee, if thy face turne from them neuer so little, they are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: but yet this is their cōfort, that thou hast care of them, when thou seemest to steepe: and indeede thou seemest to sleepe, to be careles of them, that in time of tempest and trouble they may despaire of thēselues, and flee for succour to thee. It is thy vse to cast cares vpon them,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:176864:16"/>that they may learne to cast their cares vpon thee, who ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest for them; for they are thy beloueds beloued, written by thy selfe in the booke of life, and thou canst not but care for them, whome thou hast vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>safed to write in so louing a booke; so that though the flesh, the world, and the diuell, and al the gates of hell do beat against them, yet the godly cannot but stand as sure as mount Sion; they are built vpon a rock, they shall neuer be remooued. They are thy gifts (O heauenly Father) and by thee giuen to Christ thine onely deare Sonne, salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it selfe; they are so giuen to thy sonnes charge, that yet thou cariest care of them, thou houl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:176864:16"/>them in thine almightie, fatherly, and therefore fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and safe hand, whereout no power shall be able to pluck them: O Lord, this is the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and security of thy seruants: and although I bee vnworthy of the least of thy mercies, yet thy Spirite assures mee of this my excellencie and safety in thee, so that I count by faith my sinnes no sinnes in thy sweet Sonne, made sinne for me, and feare not that wicked one, that seeketh to touch mee: I am by thy grace one of thy little Flocke, and therefore I will not feare: It is thy pleasure (O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) to giue a Kingdome, and therefore why should I feare? thy Sonne hath bought mee, his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:176864:17"/>hearts bloude was the price, his owne bloud is neere, and therefore I cannot but be deare vnto him: This is my faith, my Meditation; O Lord, I thanke thee for it, and beseech thee to continue it, thorough Iesus Christ my Lorde and Sauiour, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A praier for peace.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> LORD God of peace, the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giuer and louer of peace, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to giue peace in our daies: the Diuel, that wicked one, and auncient murtherer,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:176864:17"/>spites and persecutes the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and striues to driue her into the desart. His head is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, yet he is alwaies nibling at the womans heele: but now especially doth he roare, like a Lyon full of wrath, because he knoweth his time to be shorte. And therefore, O Lord, cut him short of his will, tread him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our feete shortly: looke not, O Lord, vppon our sinnes, but vpon thy sweete sonne. We deserue trouble and confusion, but yet for his seke be thou mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto vs, and cause thy face to shine vpon vs: take from vs all infidelitie, distrust, disobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, all hardnesse of hart, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of thy worde and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements: take al rebellion
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:176864:18"/>from vs, that we may eate the good things of the land without sworde, in peace. And to this purpose, O Lord, we pray not onely for our selues, but for our enemies, desiring thee for the time past, to pardon their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and folly; for they haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted thee, and knowe not what they haue done: it is hard for them to kicke against the pricke: he that toucheth thine annointed, toucheth thee, thy very eie. O Lord, touch them with remorse of Conscience, smite them downe as thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Saule, cal them to thy fould, and gather them that now are deuoute in scattering. And if it please thee still to suffer them to be prickes in our sides; so that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:176864:18"/>we can haue no peace with thē in thee: yet (O Lord) neuer let vs be without thee, and peace without them in thee: for hee that hath peace in thee, needeth not care how little peace he find in the world; because this world doth vanish, and thy peace en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth, and shall neuer ende Blesse vs therefore (sweet God) with peace, especially peace in thee, and with thee: so shal we be sure, that our trouble in thy good time shall cease, and wee finde euerlasting peace, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Iesus Christ, our only true peace and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:176864:19"/>
                     <head>A praier for peace of conscience.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God, I am assured by the Prophet E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>say, that there is no peace to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and indeede, where there is no true peace but in thee; so they being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst thee, and therefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee, can haue no true peace: And yet there is no peace to be had with thee, but by faith in Christ, in whom alone (the peace of all the faithfull) thou art appeased, and well pleased with the faithfull. Indeed, the wicked haue their peace, and pleasure manie times in the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:176864:19"/>world. The Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sees may agree, but yet against Christ: O Lord, send me rather warre, and a sworde then such peace with euill in euill. Giue me grace, O Lord, to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the lusts, that fight against my soule, to defie Sathan, to be hartily sorie for my sinnes, to be wearie of the body of death, to feare mine own dooings, to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire of my selfe, and raise me vp by a liuely faith, that I may be iustified, and being iust, may be at peace with thee, through Iesus Christ my Lord; who is that one, and onely seede of the woman, that hath foyled the Serpent, &amp; dissolued his works: so that now hee is but a nibler, and cannot be a conquerour of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:176864:20"/>the woman. O Lorde it is thy worke if man beleeue, work thy work in me, that I may beleeue, that thy Gospell may bee my peace and power to saue mee. And where the diuel is a prince, &amp; laieth before my conscience my manifold and grieuous sins, thy iustice &amp; zeale in punishing sin; O lord, make me strong and cheerful in faith, to lay sure hold of thy almighty mercy, which is yea and Amen, to all thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, in the dear death of thy son, which is the only death of death, &amp; merit of life euerlasting; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (O lord) giue me grace to rest, that I may liue in safety: grant this O father of mercy, for Iesus Christs sake, our only mediator and aduocate, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:176864:20"/>
                     <head>A comfortable prayer, in time of aduersitie.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Righteous God, it is thy nature, euen in thy soule to hate iniquity, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou art woont to correct thy children, and to chasten them, that so thou maiest re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime them frō iniquity, so that thy rebukes are tokens of loue, for this thy mercy, O Lord, we giue thee harty thanks. Dauid found good by thy humbling of him: and thy gold is neuer clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, then when it is tried, for then it is fined. Iohn Baptist lost no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by the losse of his head. the head Christ in heauen was
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:176864:21"/>safe, who for his sake brake the Serpents head, and will in his good time restore his head, and whole body vnto him againe, in state like to his owne glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Body: But yet, O Lord, as for the wicked who persecute vs, it is for thy quarrell, that they hate vs, they are thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and therefore keepe not silence, suppresse their rage, and saue thy Peter from their gir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles if thy good wil be so: if not; thy wil be done, that thou mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est be either by life, or death ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage to him. Giue vs grace that the wicked, can onely kill the bodye, and not the bodie without thy sufferance, who sufferest thine to bee tried no further then shall fall out for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:176864:21"/>their good, for death it selfe to them in thee, is as it was to Paule, a dissolution, a desired sleepe, no death but a steppe to eternall life: it is but a separation of their bodies, and soules for a time, which shal be coupled a gaine, neuer to be put in sunder, but to be glorified together in heauen for euer. O Lord, let this be my comfort in all time of discomfort, through Iesus Christ our Lord: to whom with thee, and the holy ghost, be all honour and glorie, worlde without end, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:176864:22"/>
                     <head>A prayer against despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God, the Father of mercie, be merciful to mee a Sinner; though my sinnes be manie and greeuous, yet thy Grace hath superabounded where sinne did abound: yea, thou art that God of loue, which diddest send thine onelie sonne into the world, by his poorenes, to enrich; by his bands to free; by his smiting to spare; by his condemning to absolue; by his deare death and passion to faue; not the iust, but greeued sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. It is my comfort that hee came to heale, not the sounde,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:176864:22"/>but the sicke: to call, not the righteous, but sinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. O Lorde, I trust not in my selfe, I am sore, I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my sinnes, I haue no hope of health or safetie for my soule, but in the sorrowes of thy sons sweete soule: (O Lord) be thou faithfull and iust to forgiue mee my sinnes, and to cleanse mee from vnrighteousnes; thy mercy bestowed vpon the dog of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, vpon Marie Magdalen, vpon Peter thy denier, Paul a chiefe sinner, the lost groates finding, the straie sheepes sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, the Samaritans Oile and Vnguent, staie me from despai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and guide mee, to cast all my affiance in thee, who art the God of compassion, and hast
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:176864:23"/>the peace of fauour, for all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed sinners, who in faith make recourse to thee for thy fauour, as thou hast not onelie promised, but sworne thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to such: I grounding my selfe vpon thy power and will, which I am assured of by thy word and oath, I denie, &amp; defie Satan, and rest bould against all my foes bodily or ghostly. This is my onely comfort, O Lorde, that my comfort may increase (sweet Lord) increase my faith, and continue my course in the same, that I may bee blessed, with thy blessed ones, in thee my good God, whose name be blessed now and euer, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:176864:23"/>
                     <head>A praier for Parents.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, thou fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of fathers, wee beseech thee, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to giue vs thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hearts, for thy goodnesse, in respect of our owne selues, but also in respect of our children, the fruite of the wombe is thy gift, and singular worke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thy church is enlarged, and continued vpon the face of the earth. O Lorde, therefore giue vs grace, to vse our children, as thy giftes, that wee may carry godly care towards them, as to teach them to remember thee their Creator, euen from the daies of their youth: for thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:176864:24"/>seruant iustifieth only, not all but many, and those onely who haue the true knowledge of him. Most parents regard na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and drawen with blind &amp; cruell loue, prouide only for the body, for the health, wealth, &amp; worldly promotion of their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: But (sweet Lord) what is it to leaue vnto them the whole world, if at length they loose their owne soules? And there fore giue vs thy grace, that wee may be their parents in respect, not only of nature, but grace, to bring them vp in thy feare and loue, that we with them maie liue with thee, and together en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioye life euerlasting, thorough Iesus Christ our Lord, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:176864:24"/>
                     <head>A prayer for a married man.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Gratious God, and louer of mankind, the first founder of marriage, I beseech thee to giue me thy grace, that I may cary iust care, no way to disgrace so honourable a state, assist me with thy spirit, that I may loue my wife, as not ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from me, but one of mee, and with me: Giue her also, O Lorde, a due regard of her cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to be my comfort, and hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, in my vocation. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause the Diuell is busie and craftie, and oftentimes vseth the woman, to the hurt of man, as appeareth not onely by Iohn
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:176864:25"/>Baptist, Dauid, and Solomon; but also by Naboth, Iob, and A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dam, our generall father: I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily beseech thee to guide my wife in better course than Eue her mother tooke before her; saue hir from temptation, and tempting of me, and let hir bee my fellow helper in all thinges, but especially in thy seruice: and if it bee thy will make hir a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and mee a Father of such children as may do thy wil, that they may bee thy Brethren, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters, and mothers; so shall they be sure to be loued of thee, and loued euerlastingly, which is the onely true ioy of Parentes, and children: grant this, O Lord, in Iesus Christ, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:176864:25"/>
                     <head>A Prayer for a marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Woman.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, although the woman first fell, yet it was thy singular mercy, to comfort her in thine owne and only son, who became man, of the seede of a woman betrothed to a hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bād, she was thy seruant, &amp; low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handmaid. The consideration of the son, doth assure me of the high honour of mariage, and the vertues of the mother were fit ornaments for a state so honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. O Lord, make and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue mee fit for such a calling, wherein it pleased thy son to be borne. I see much contempt in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:176864:26"/>this miserable day of so holie an ordinance, by outrage of lusts: fornication and all vncleannes ought not once to be named a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thy Saintes: it doth not them: our bed ought to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defiled, and the bodies of thy seruants ought to be kept pure, as members of thy son, and fitte temples for thy Spirit. But (O Lord) thou knowest all, I mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable wretch am before thine eies, and humbly intreat thee to confirme me against all disgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of marriage, thy holy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. Giue me grace to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the soosenes of our daies, to pittie them that amend not, to praie for their amendment, to keepe my selfe purely religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, &amp; vnspotted: yea to detest
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:176864:26"/>the breach of wedlocke as the diuel: for it is a vile, a shamefull &amp; pernitious euill; it ouerthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth priuate persons, whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, yea, whole kingdomes: it destroieth mens bodies, yea, and soules. O Lord, therefore deliuer mee from this euill, for Iesus Christs sake, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for Chastitie.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, the bodies of Christians are the Temples of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghost, and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse becommeth the house of so holy a spirit, giue me grace to keepe my selfe holy to thee: set Ioseph before mine eies: if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:176864:27"/>tempter tempt me, let me as Ioseph did, lesse esteeme perill of body, then losse of my Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitie: So did Susanna, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded her Chastity more then her life: giue me the like grace O Lord, for nothing is gained but wrath, by fauoring and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the lusts of the flesh. To this purpose I reade of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Sodom, nay, the whole world was drowned for this sin, and these examples with others are written for our learning, that we should by these and the like iudgements learne to flee al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fornication, and lustes, for feare of thy iudgements. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let me be one of thy virgins, whether I be vnmaried, or mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, to keepe my selfe and my
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:176864:27"/>bed vndefiled, that I may bee one with virgins to followe Christ, my Lambe in heauen, wheresoeuer he goeth. Graunt this (O Father) for Iesus Christs sake, our mediatour and Aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A praier for a woman great with childe.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord. great, and yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued is the paine and perill of child-bearing: I beseech thee to forgiue the cause, which is my sinne, and ease me of the paine, that sinne doth merite. In the paine I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the vilenes of sinne, the vprightnes of thy iustice: O
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:176864:28"/>Lorde temper thy iudgement with mercy towards me; if it be thy good wil, grant me spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and safe deliuerance: the fruite of the wombe is thy mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous worke: O Lorde haue care of thine owne, and make mee a ioifull mother in thee. Giue mee care to take due care of thy worke; grant my childe life and health, if thy pleasure be so, if not, O Lorde, I am in thy handes, and commit both my selfe and my childe into thy hands, to deale with vs accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy mercie, desiring thee both in life and death, to be an aduantage to vs both, that whether we liue or die, we may be thine: grant this, O Father, for thy Sons sake, Iesus Christ
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:176864:28"/>our Lorde, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for Children.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hy Scripture, O lord, vvritten vvith thine owne hande, doeth charge me to honour, father, and mother; nay, this is the first commandement with promise. O Lord, giue me this grace, first to serue thee, and in thee, to obey them, that it may be well with me, and that I may liue long on the earth: and so moderate my parents, O Lord, that they prouoke mee not to wrath, but may carry that iust care which belongeth vnto them, to bring me vp in instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:176864:29"/>and information of thee to traine me vppe in thy worde, which is truth, and able to make mee wise to saluation. Make me (O Lord) a Timothy, a The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophilus, that I may honour, and loue thee, and so liue in thy loue which is assured to al them that loue thee, who art loue; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause thy loue can be deserued, but yet is of thine vndeserued grace promised to all such as liuing doe loue thee. O Lorde, thou hast done wondrous things for me, to frame me in my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, to nourish mee before, and since I was borne, to suffer me to be the childe of christian parents, to liue in time of the free course of the gospell. I haue no friend in heauen or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:176864:29"/>earth like vnto thee, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore giue my parents grace to be thankfull for me, and make me thankefull for my selfe, to doe whatsoeuer thou commandest. Assist me euer with the strength of thy spirit, that I may hate and shunne all the vanities of youth, that being a childe by nature, yet I may be olde in grace and care of duety, to the perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of my holy oath in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme, whereby I am bound to thee (O God) to forsake sinne, &amp; to serue thee as wholy thine. O Lorde, I am thy worke, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and continue in mee, a true heart, that I may walke as one created to good workes, which thou hast prepared for thine to walke in. Giue me grace to be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:176864:30"/>holy in my thoughtes, holy in my wordes, holy in my waies, that I may haue the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble witnesse of conscience, that I am thy childe, who art father onely to thy secret, and holie ones. This (O Lorde) I beseech thee to grant, for thy sons sake, who liueth and raigneth with thee, world without ende, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maisters.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, forasmuch as we haue charge of children, who are thy gifts; giue vs harty and earnest care of their education, not only
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:176864:30"/>to bring them vp in ciuilitie fit for this worlde, but to ground them in sound christianity, as fit for thee and thy Church, which it hath pleased thee to choose out of the world. And whereas most of vs make no account of their religion, so we traine them vp in humane learning; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny care for nothing so they may gaine by their profession: O Lord, and maister of all, teach them that are such, better les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and giue me a better care of my calling, that my schollers may be thy schollers, no liers, where thou art truth, no swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers where thou hast giuen this lesson, sweare not at all, not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to sinne, where thou hast charged all to keepe thy lawe,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:176864:31"/>which forbiddeth all sinne: so shall I haue Christian schollers, and be a ioyfull Maister of good Children, to my comfort, and thy praise; through Iesus Christ our Lord, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for Schollers.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL good giftes come from thee (O Father in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen) and without thee we can doe nothing; we beseech thee to frame our willes to learne what is profitable for vs; but aboue all thinges howe to serue and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:176864:31"/>please thee: for all learning is folly, if it be not directed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy will, and to keepe the glorie of thy name. And therefore blesse our Parentes, with sufficient store and care to bring vs vppe vnder Christian Tutors, in thy faith; and feare vs with a duetifull regarde of our time, that we spende it to their comfort, our owne good, and to the increase of thy Church, to the honour, and praise of thy name; thorough Iesus Christ our Lorde and only life, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:176864:32"/>
                     <head>A praier for Maisters of families.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, it hath pleased thee to make vs maisters on earth, giue vs grace to discharge it, guide vs from threatning contempt, and detaining of dues, remembring that there is no respect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons with thee, who art also our maister: yea, O Lord, they are Chickens of thy Henne, and Lambes of the Shepheard of Soules: be they neuer so poore, yet are they chosen to be rich in faith, and coheires of thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome with thine onely heire, as well as others. And therefore
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:176864:32"/>giue me godly care to esteeme of them as of my seruants, and yet thy heires: giue them grace to serue thee first, and me in thee; and strength me so, that I may account of them in thee, not as flaues, but as christians, &amp; brethren. And to that purpose (O Lord) let me haue thy feare before mine eies, not onely to require of them the seruice of their bodies, but thy seruice in spirit and truth, to the sauing of their soules, discharge of my conscience, and praise of thy name; thorough Iesus Christ our Lord, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:176864:33"/>
                     <head>A prayer for Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lorde God, thou art the Lord of all, and all estates de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vppon thee, giue me grace to doe my dutie, so to serue men, that I maie serue thee. Grant (O Lord) to my Maister and Mistris, that they maie doe vnto mee, that which is iust and equall, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that thou art, not only ours, but their Maister in Heauen: and assist me with thy spirite and grace, that I maie be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to thee in all thinges not with eie seruice, as a pleaser of man, but in singlenesse of hart,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:176864:33"/>fearing God; that whatsoeuer I doe, I may doe it heartilie, as to thee, and not to men, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that I shall receiue a reward of the inheritaunce, as the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of the Lord Christ Iesus, in whose name onely I craue sufficient grace for my calling, that I may be thine in all dutie, to my comfort, and thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for the good bringing vp of children.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hildren (O Lord) are thy speciall Blessing, thy Church consisteth of them, and is continued in them. That they may be holy, fitte
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:176864:34"/>members of thy Church: thy holy Church admitteth none as appertaining, but such as being baptized, vow to thee to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as thou (O God) art holy. Blesse therfore this good course of thy Church, and giue all thy people care of their children, that they be apt Seminaries of Christians. Let them neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thy commandement giuen by Moses, that they are to teach their Children, not what they please, but may please thee. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid being neare his death, for a worthy farewell, did diligently instruct his son &amp; heire apparāt, Solomon: Susanna had such pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents as brought her vp accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the law of Moses: That worthy mother exhorted her
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:176864:34"/>seauen sonnes to die in thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they should denie thee: To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bias the elder taught his sonne to feare God, euen from his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie: O Lord, send vs many elect Ladies, and send them such sonnes as may walke in thy trueth: Fill thy Church full of Timothees; that so we may be parents of soules, as well as of bodies; to thy glory and our comfort, thorough Iesus Christ our Lord, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for Watchfulnesse against Satan.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous father, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est whereof I am made,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:176864:35"/>I am dust, a fraile creature, sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to sinne, and by course of corrupt nature, onely giuen to Sinne: I am not able so much as to thinke any good of my selfe: this is my wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched case (O God.) But yet, alas, wretch that I am, I am not so weake, but my enemie is as strong, he is a Lyon, yea he is mercilesse, hee hungers, he roares, he gapes, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passeth euerie waie to vse my weakenesse to my owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction. Giue me grace there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to bee sober, and watch, that I enter not into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: let not that wicked one touch me, and if he touch me with sinne, which for this life cannot but be in mee; yet let
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:176864:35"/>him not touch me so, that my sinne be mortall to me. O Lord, consider my desire, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to my prayer: the Diuell neuer sleepes, he is neuer idle, hee watcheth against me wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and sleeping: O God, therefore let not thine eyes close; watch for mee, and let mee watch in thee, that the Diuell maie haue no domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ouer me: keepe mee (O Lord) from presumptuous sins, and though sinne be in me, yet let it not raigne, but make me strong against it, thorough Iesus Christ my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:176864:36"/>
                     <head>A necessary prayer for our time, and for all Christians.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E thanke thee, O gratious God, for all thy goodnesse bestowed vppon vs; for of thy ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse it is, that wee haue either nature, or grace, for without thee, we were nothing: and yet thou madest vs something; nay, thou diddest create all thinges before vs, and for vs; and at last thou madest man, after thine owne Image, like to thy selfe, and prince of all beasts, fowles, and fishes. Nay, wherein, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with our first parentes, (in whose person, all mankind was
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:176864:36"/>included) wee disgraced our selues, displeasing thee, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring thy iust offence; so that thou mightest haue cast vs into hell fire, which neuer shall bee quenched: yet it was thy good pleasure to pitie vs, and of thine infinite pitie to send into this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill world, thine owne and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie naturall Image, Christ Iesu, thy dearelie beloued, and onely begotten sonne, to restore vs to thine Image againe. Yea, hee came being God, to bee man, not by deposition of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, but by assumption of true manhood; that being one with GOD, who was offended, he might be one with vs, who had offended; and by the passions of his guiltles manhood, ioined to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:176864:37"/>the infinite might of his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, hee might remooue our guiltshippe from vs, and set vs at one with God. O immortall God, for these thy woonderous fauours, we giue thee immortall thankes: but yet alas, how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefull are wee, who for all this thy loue, do not loue thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? For the Oxe knoweth his owner, and the Asse his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters cribbe: but we knowe not thee, we do not vnderstand, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somuch that Heauen and earth may be called vppon to witnes of our miserable vnthankfulnes. For as for this our Realme of England, thou hast beene euery waie a Father, and fauourable vnto vs the inhabitants thereof; thou hast not dealt so gratiously
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:176864:37"/>with any people liuing, as thou hast doone with vs: and yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, what are we but a sinfull na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a people laden with iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, a seed of the wicked, corrupt children? do wee not prouoke thee to wrath? thou hast smitten vs in these respects, but yet most gently: and yet alas, we make none vse of thy fauourable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes, which are argumentes of thy loue; for we fall away more and more. Nay alas, the whole heade is sicke, and the whole heart is heauy, from the sole of the foot to the head, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing whole therein; but wounds, and swelling, and sores full of corruption. O Lord, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what maie wee looke for, but to haue our Land wast, our
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:176864:38"/>riches burnt with fire, strangers to deuour our Land in our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, to see it desolate, like the ouerthrow of strangers. This, O Lord, we deserue; but yet we beseech thee, O Lord, to spare vs: and to that purpose, O Lord, wash vs, make vs cleane; take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the euill of our works from before thine eies: giue vs grace to cease to do euill, teach vs our lesson to learne to doe well, to seeke iudgement, to releeue the oppressed, to iudge the fatherles, to defend the Widow, to be so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for our sinnes, to amend our liues, to he are thy voice, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the same: to consent, &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, that we may eate the good things of the Land, and bee sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the deuouring sword.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:176864:38"/>O Lord make our Crimson sins as white as Snow, let our Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let sinnes, be as Wooll, through Iesus Christ our only sauior, and redeemer, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <p>O LORD, we haue sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: nay alas, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of our daies are proud in their sinnes, and all that doe wickedlie are stubble before thee: if thou wouldest thou coul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dest send vpon a day that should burne vs as an Ouen, and leaue neither roote nor branch: but yet, O Lord, thou art a pitifull God, and giuest vs space to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Giue vs grace to know the day of thy patience, to redeeme
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:176864:39"/>the time, to looke to our steps, to walke more warely than as yet we haue done, that we may escape the great and fearefull daie, which is the daie of thy wrath, wherein the wicked shal not be able to stand. For thine owne sake, O Lorde, make vs not to be despised, and vile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all people: but be thou our Father, prepare vs to walke in the waie before thee; let vs bee vnto thee a flocke, and spare vs as a man spareth his owne sonne that serueth him. Conuert (O Lord) the wicked, or if that bee not thy wil, confound them, that say: it is in vaine to serue thee, and that there is no profite in keeping thy commandements, or in walking humblie bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:176864:39"/>thee. O Lorde, giue mee grace to hate them that hate thee, and to be a companion of them onely that feare thee, that liuing in righteousnesse, I maie liue without feare before thee al the daies of my life. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it is the innocent that shal deliuer England, and the safety of al places and persons, resteth not in the arme, or wisedome of flesh and bloud, but only in thy faith and seruice: I pray, O Lord, not onely for my selfe, but for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, desiring thee to increase Lots little family, that so thy mercies may bee continued to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, which yet the worlde now no better then Sodome contemneth, crying peace to it selfe, where there can bee no
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:176864:40"/>peace to a Sodome, if Lot bee not in Sodome. Increase there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, O Lorde, thy kingdome; clocke and call many chickens vnder the winges of thy son. Let him be our Hen, and let vs haue will and heart to kisse him, that we may be safe vnder him, who is thy saluation: Grant this, O Father, for his sake, Amen,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for Preachers.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord of the haruest, I humblie thanke thee, that thou hast vouchsafed me this high honour, to bee one of thy labourers, vnworthy (O Lord) I am, to vnloose the latchet of thy
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:176864:40"/>shoe: but yet by thy grace, I am that I am; I beseech thee let not thy grace be vaine in me. Giue me thine assistance (O Lord) that I be thankfull, bold, and wise, to do thy will; keepe me from speaking any lie in thy name; guide my mouth to speake nothing, but from thy mouth, that so he that heareth mee, may heare thee. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause nothing disgraceth the course of thy gospell more than life repugnant to thy word, and I by thy word am a light of the world, strengthen me with the light of thy grace, that my light may shine by good workes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore men, to the discharge of my dutie, the confirmation of thy weake ones, the confusion
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:176864:41"/>of thy foes, &amp; to thy glory. Let me be one of thy voices, to crie for amendment; and not onely by word, but by workes, liuing as becommeth thy Gospell, (which is thy power to saue thē that beleeue, and therfore such onely as make proofe by godly life of their beliefe) least while I preach to others, I my selfe bee reprooued; rather (O Lord) let me beat downe sinne, and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the world to my selfe, and my selfe to the world. Graunt this, O Father, for Iesus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes sake, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <p>O Father of heauen, light it selfe, in whom there is no
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:176864:41"/>darkenesse at all, it hath pleased thee to call me most vnworthy of the least of thy mercies, yet to be partaker of the light of thy Gospell, and by thy Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to be a light to the blinde and ignorant.</p>
                     <p>O Lorde, therefore be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to mee, open mine eies that I may see, and my mouth that I may speake, and my heart that I may beleeue nothing but thy truth. Giue mee grace no way to feare flesh, and bloud, but with courage to fight out my fight, and finish my course: and where he that doth euil, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thy light, blesse me so, that I may hate, defy, and contemne the hatred and pride of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. Moses checkt Pharao,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:176864:42"/>Elias checkt Achab, Helizeus spared not Ioram, the Prophet spared not Ieroboam, Iohn Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tist rebuked Herode, and Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen thy seruant, was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to checke and chide the Iewes. Giue me (O Lord) the same spirit of constancie, and bouldnesse, to contemne the threatnings, and crackes of the wicked: be thou with me, and my comforter, against all those that cānot away with thy word, and ministers thereof. And if thy good will be so, graunt thy word a full and free course, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert the hearts of sinners vnto thee, seeke the lost groate, giue the prodigall sonne grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, to come to thee to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse his sinnes, that he maie tast
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:176864:42"/>of thee how good thou art, if it be thy will: graunt this (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee) in Iesus Christ our Lord and Sauiour, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer after the hearing of the word preached.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough Paul plāt, and Apollo doe water; yet O lord, all is nothing without thee, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les thou giue grace, wee cannot beare awaie the fruite of thy word: wee beseech thee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of thy great mercie, to make vs alwaies profiting hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, as chickens to come vnto
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:176864:43"/>thee at thy call. O Lord, let me not bee graue in profession, and drie in conuersation: I knowe that greene Leaues cannot please thee, faith and figges thou doest require; make mee apt and able to do thy will, for that (sweete God) is all my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire: it is a thing that makes thy name blasphemed, because we haue much profession, &amp; small proofe. O Lord take awaie this shame of our time, and so guide me to professe, that I maie in life expresse; so to heare, that I may follow; that my fruits maie wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to mee, and to the worlde, that I am one of thy good trees, safe from hewing downe and burning, sure to grow, &amp; florish in heauen with Christ Iesus, for
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:176864:43"/>whose sake grant this, O father of mercie, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A thankesgiuing to God for his benefites.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E is not, O Lord, fit to receiue new blessings, that wil not be thankefull to thee for recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued blessings: Iacob was blessed by thee, and hee was thankefull: thou diddest deliuer Israel out of Aegypt, it was thy wil it should bee remembred; when Moyses and thy children had passed the red sea, they did sing vnto thee; when Tobias had receiued his sight, his wife, and all his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintaunce
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:176864:44"/>glorified thee. O Lorde God, the Scriptures are full of thy gratiousnesse, and of thy seruants thankfulnes: surelie thou hast been in as great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure gratious to vs, thy people of England, as euer thou wast to the people of anie Nation: wee haue beene vnworthie of the least of thy mercies, giue vs grace to be Iacobs: wee haue by thee escaped the darkenesse, and bondage of Aegypt of Rome; giue vs grace to sing as Moyses did, with thy people a song of praise for our deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: thou hast graunted vs, not onelie with Tobias the sight of the bodie, but of thy will in thy worde our light, and by the red Sea, the pretious bloud of thy
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:176864:44"/>Sonne, our only and most deere Captaine, we haue escaped not a mortall, but an immortall Pharao, the diuell himselfe. And therefore (O Lord God) we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee, to giue vs soft and thankefull heartes; for these thy mercies be manie, and maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and deserue thankes. Wee aske this grace of thee in the name of thy sonne Iesus Christ, our onelie mediator and aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate: to whome with thee, and the holie Ghost, be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie, now and for euer, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:176864:45"/>
                     <head>A prayer for the feare of God.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL Christians (O Lorde) are bounde to feare thee, for with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thy feare (O lord) there is no wisedome, but follie and perill of soule; for the defect of thy feare is the cause of sinne. And therefore Abraham coulde say to Abimilech, I thought in my selfe, saying: Perhaps the feare of God is not in this place, and they will slaie me. O Lord, therefore keepe mee from this people, and places where thy feare is not: for thy blessing and grace followeth them that feare thee, and first seeke thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:176864:45"/>The Midwiues of Egypt, the fame of Iudith widow, the manifold blessings powred vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon thy seruants, fearing thee doe prooue it: in this respect thy worde commendeth Simeon, <hi>Luke 2. Cornelius, Acts, 9. Iob.</hi> and others. Oh, therefore blesse me so, that I may feare thee, and fearing thee, that I may worke righteousnesse, that so I may bee accepted of thee; yea (O Lord) strengthen me, so that I feare no man, but as farre foorth as in fearing thee, I maie feare thee: so shall I be sure to liue without feare of them, who can onely kill the bodie; yea, and without feare of Satan, who can doe nothing against them that feare thee, but as thou shalt
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:176864:46"/>please to giue him seaue to their good, and the Diuels further confusion, as thou diddest suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him against thy seruant Iob: who fearing thee, was secure in thee, to the Diuels shame, his owne comfort, the Churches confirmatiō in patience, against passions be they neuer so grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, to thine immortall praise, and glory, through Iesus Christ our Lord and Sauiour, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for courage against the feare of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lorde God of hostes, thou God to whome power belongeth, giue
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:176864:46"/>me grace, not onely to professe, but in life to expresse the Faith of Abraham; to bee a Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neel, an Israelite indeede; to be a man after thy heart, as was thy seruant Dauid: be with me (O Lord) in all that I doe, then shall I not need to feare, what flesh can do to me. The words of Abimelech to Abraham do prooue this point vnto me, that thine assistance is able to secure, yea, and to make the wicked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide of them. And therefore Abimelech coulde say vnto A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham: God is with thee in all thou doest; sweare therefore to God, that thou hurt mee not. Thus when the Egyptians pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued after the children of Israel, accounting of their ouerthrow;
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:176864:47"/>yet when they saw the vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querable power in conducting them thorow the red sea, they could say, Let vs flee from Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, for God fighteth for them: and so did Saule (O Lord) feare thy Dauid, when he saw thou wast with him O Lord be thou likewise with me, &amp; the whole land, wherein I liue, strike thy feare into the hearts of all those Egyptians of Rome, Spaine, &amp; other places that groane day and night, to make hauocke of thy people. Saue vs by land &amp; water; let them know that thou fightest for vs. O strike thy feare into the hearts of all, that feare thee not, but are enemies to all them, that feare thee; that so the Diuell may be ashamed of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:176864:47"/>his attempts, thy Church maie increase, and we sing vnto thee iust and immortall praise, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Iesus Christ our Lorde, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A praier for Patience.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, where mans life is full of trouble and danger, and thy Children are sore, and continually assaulted, not onely by flesh and bloud, but with the Diuell, who is a power, principalitie, and spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall wickednesse: I beseech thee, by thy spirit to assist, that I may resist the Diuell, and he may flee from me. Iob thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:176864:48"/>was sore thrust at, afflicted in body, depriued of his childrē, spoiled of al his goods; yet could he say that hee would trust in thee, although thou wouldest kil him: Tobias was greatly tēp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, when his owne parentes could flout at his almes and his hope; and yet was he bould to checke them with patience: Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanna thy seruant was vniustlie defamed and charged, and yet is it saide of her, that her heart was fixed on thee. O Lorde, howsoeuer it shall please thee, to lay thine hand vpon me: yet graunt me patience to endure thy triall, that continuing thine to the ende, I may bee thine, worlde without end, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:176864:48"/>
                     <head>A prayer against pride.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Angell (O lord) was for his pride cast out of heauen; &amp; where man had principalitie giuen vnto him ouer Fishes, Foules, and Beasts; yet the Diuel in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents shape, tempted, and Eue consented to eat of the fruit for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, so that pride was her fal: she offended God, and became captiue to sinne, by seeking to be God: with this sin was Saule infected, and therfore he would needs haue Samuel to honour him before the elders of the people. O Lord, the world is full of diuers possessed with it:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:176864:49"/>But what did pride profit any of them? Proud Aman gained a paire of gallowes: Nabuchodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizor would needs be like vnto the highest, and became like vnto a beast: Antiochus &amp; He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod were deuoured of wormes. when the Disciples saide vnto Christ, Diuels are subiect to vs in thy name; Christ checkt thē saying: I saw Sathan like light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fall from heauen. O Lord, saue me frō so vile a sin, giue me grace to remember what I am: for I am dust, and ashes; and what cause hath dust to bee proud? Let me neuer (O Lord) forget the humility of the Saints thy seruants: but especially of thy chiefe seruant, my Sauiour Iesus Christ, who was content
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:176864:49"/>to be a seruant to man, to wash till it came to his disciples feete, in water: and not onely so, but also their bodies, and soules, in his pretious bloud: O Lorde, make me a Lambe of thy folde; bring me vnto thy Christ, who was that Lambe, that by his owne example doth charge me &amp; all christians, saying, Be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp; meeke as I am: Strike in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me (O Lord) care of this du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and giue them grace to bee ashamed of pride, who are dust, where thy sonne was humble, and humbled to the death, euen the death of the Crosse, to saue vs from death. Assist mee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, to submit my selfe vnder thy mighty hande, whereunto all creatures doe bow. O Lord,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:176864:50"/>blesse me with a broken, and contrite heart, that thou maiest be my health against Sathan; let me be poore in spirit, that I may be sure to bee blessed in thee, who art God blessed for euer, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer against sinfull anger.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, saue me from the danger of the wicked: they are angry with that which is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing to thee. Caine spited Abel, for his seruing of thee: and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam cannot blesse Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but Balac is offended: It
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:176864:50"/>displeased Saule, that Dauid af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conquest was commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: Naaman disliketh the good coūsel of Elizeus: so did A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a of the Prophet Hanani: Nay, alas, Paule could not withdraw the people from the worship of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana, and of gods made with hands, indeed no gods, but De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius angry. O Lord, this is worldly anger, and their dislike, who like all things, but thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie &amp; their own saluation. If anie Tobias doe speake against theft, or any sinne; O Lord, giue me grace to vse my selfe better, then did the wife of Tobias: not to bee angry, but glad of such a friend, whose buffets are euer better, then the Oyle of the flatterer; who deceiuing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:176864:51"/>deceiueth others, running and causing others to run head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into destruction: for hee that is angry with my sinne, is angry with my mortall enemy. And therefore giue me grace to be thankefull for such a one, and while I liue (O Lord) send me such friends, as will not be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with that, that good is, but that which naught is in me: and giue me grace to be such a one to others; so wilt thou (O Lord) be no God of anger, but a God of loue vnto me. Which grant that I may liue by thy loue, who art my only loue, in Christ thy dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:176864:51"/>
                     <head>A prayer for Godly anger.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is thy will (O Lord) that I should be angry, but not sinne; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore giue me grace to be angry, but not to sin. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses was angrye with Pharao, when hee sawe that Pharao would not heare him: Ionathan was angry with his owne father Saule, he would not eat for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to consider his fathers wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked minde against Dauid: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemias was angry, when hee heard the out-cries of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who were pressed with V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sury: nay, good Dauid was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:176864:52"/>with the man, indeed with himselfe, whome the Prophet touched so priuily by a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Giue me grace (O Lord) likewise to be angry, not with thy creature, but with the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of thy creature, to hate sinne in others, yea, and in my selfe: for if sinne displease me, I am sure to please thee, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test nothing, no not in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, but sinne. And in that res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, strengthen me so farre, as to condemne, yea, and to cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie the body of sinne, to the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of my duty, comfort of mine owne conscience, and praise of thy name; thorough Iesus Christ our Lorde and Sauiour, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:176864:52"/>
                     <head>A prayer against Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ature, O Lord, is content with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; and therefore it is against nature to exceede: yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasse, such is the corruption of man, that not onlie the wicked, but thy seruants often times doe exceede: Esau solde his Birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right for a messe of Pottage; the rich glutton lost his soule by it; it brought the prodigal sonne to beggerie. Nay (alas) it was the sinne of thine owne people: Lot, Noe, our first parents offended, breaking Christian measure in meate and drink: a grieuous sin,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:176864:53"/>O Lord it is, to abuse thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to breake thy will against nature, tending to the weaknes of nature, discredite of christian profession, and perill of soules. Adam and Eue were sore pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished for it; it was one cause of the drowning of the world, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Sodome: For this sinne the houses fell vppon the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines, while they were ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetting, and making merry. It was an occasion of Amons and Holofernes death: Nay (alasse) thou, O Lord, dost not only pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish it temporallie, but eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, in all those that without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance runne on in excesse, as though they were <hi>fruges consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere nati,</hi> borne to be wasters. O Lord, I reade it will be suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:176864:53"/>cause to condemne a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked man, if he do not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his abilitie feede thee in thy hungrie, and relieue thee in thy wanting members. Alas, then what wil become of them, that make no account of thy blessinges? but are giuen by vaine excesse to make wast of them; which might according to thy will, charitablie be besto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vppon thee in thy needie feruants: And yet (alas) what sin is more common in this our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable daies, wherein we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not meete neighbourly without course, indeed without excesse out of course; in which respect, if God plague the whole land with dearth and death, to teach vs, to carie more due regarde of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:176864:54"/>his blessings, it is no maruell. O Lord, keepe mee from affecting or fauouring this kind of sinne in my selfe, or anie others; giue me grace to dislike it, condemne it at all times: but especiallie at such times, as by thy Church are ordained for abstinence, iustlie binding vs by order to some ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinence, who of our selues woulde neuer liue in compasse. And to this purpose giue the Magistrate care to execute, and me to performe this point of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary duety, to the beating downe of the flesh, and lusts of the same: grant this, O fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for Christes sake, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:176864:54"/>
                     <head>A prayer against coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tousnesse.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Aked, O Lorde, I came into the world, and naked I shall returne to the earth, from whence I came: giue me sufficient (O Lord) that I may serue thee, and my dayly bread let me neuer want. Giue me grace first to seeke thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the righteousnesse thereof; so shall I be sure neuer to want. And if it please thee to blesse me with riches (O Lord) forbid that my heart should bee cast vpon them; but rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline me in charitie, which is the badge of thy Children, to bee
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:176864:55"/>good to all, euen to mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: but especially to the poore of thy housholde, that being a faithfull seruaunt, I may lay out my Talent to gaine: and by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of my riches (thy benefites) to the poore, I may bee rich in good works: for what is all the world to a man, if hee bee not rich in thee; and what is it, to be a begger, euen of a crumme of bread? All riches without thee are nothing: Diues proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it, they could not saue him from hell: all want hurteth not, if a man be rich in thee. Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus was not worth a crumme of bread; and yet his want could not barre him from heauen: he that is thy seruant, be hee neuer so poore, he onely is rich. And
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:176864:55"/>therefore saue me, O Lord, from the sinne of couetousnes, and let me couet onely after thee: tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Iesus Christ my Lorde, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer against bribes.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ribes (O Lord) are called the rewarde of iniquitie, and it is written, that Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam loued the same: I beseech thee saue me from all tempting Balacs, and bribing Merchants: or if they attempt to corrupt me, yet (O Father) which art in heauen, deliuer me from euill, and tempting diuell. Giue mee better grace than Balaam had,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:176864:56"/>not to loue, but to hate the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of iniquitie. For what commeth of such bribetaking? Iudgement is peruerted: it is founde true in the sonnes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel. What commeth of it, but deceit and danger? Dalila pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it, and Sampson felt it; Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hezi was plagued for it. The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell (O Lord) by this sinne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth gouernours the compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of theeues: by this sinne hee tempted to drawe thy Daniell from thee: yea, he offred thine onely son, the heire of al things, all the kingdomes of the world, to forsake thee. O Lord, he that tempted him, will not spare to tempt them that be his: and therefore I beseech thee to giue thy grace to me, and to all thy
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:176864:56"/>people, but especially to them that be in authority, to bid satan auaunt, and with Daniel to set naught by the offer of Baltha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer, or bad men whatsoeuer: for what is it to gaine a whole world, and to loose our soules? Assist me therefore with thy spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that I may cary such speciall care of my soule, that no reward of iniquitie may draw me from that duty, which I haue vowed to thee in heauen. And as for them that bee great men, and Gods among men, strike this consideration into them, that if they bee takers of bribes, they will proue no Gods but Idols, and diuels companions in hell. Keepe and sweepe Simon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus out of thy Church, whereso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:176864:57"/>he liues: giue all thy Pauls grace to follow Paul, if any Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix, or any other looke for a bribe, yet to offer nothing. Saue al thy people from this grieuous sinne, for Iesus Christes sake, our only mediatour, and aduocate, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer against discord and malice.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Gracious God, thou art the God of loue and peace, and thy blessing is vpon the peacemaker, and man that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thee, and man in thee: keepe mee from all hatred and malice: bow my hart (O Lord)
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:176864:57"/>to keepe thy commandements of loue, and let my condition be rather to be an Abel, and hated, then a Caine to hate. Giue mee grace to beleeue in thy iust son, that my workes may bee iust to please thee, and all, but that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>please thee. Saue me from the peace of the wicked, who haue no peace that good is; because they haue no peace with thee, who art only good: but let mee be zealous of peace and vnitie with them that are thine. Dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion (O Lord) is a rent, that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth not only priuate state, but whole kingdomes: and therefore for the surer and larger propagation of thy kingdome; giue me thy grace, as also to all them that professe thy holie
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:176864:58"/>name, that we may liue in ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full loue, as brethren, not only in nature, but grace. I read, that thine owne children haue sometimes iarred so farre, that Abraham and Lot coulde not dwell in one place together. If the like infirmitie fall vppon vs, that fell vpon our father A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham: giue vs grace to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his example, to compose all quarrels, to forgiue, and forget, no waie to breake the bonde of peace; or if wee doe, yet with true repentance, and vnfained hearts, to knitte the same againe: that so wee may be fit seruants for thee, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more the glorie of thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome on earth, which no way is hindered more, then with iar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:176864:58"/>In this respect (O Lorde) conuert, or if that bee not thy will, confound all the brawling Spirites of our miserable time; Atheists, Papists, Anabaptists, Brownists, Barrowists, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, Schismatiques and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines whatsoeuer, who by profession, penne and practise, disquiet thy Church, and stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die nothing else, but how to rent it in pieces: And indue all thy people with the spirite of Loue, that seruing thee the God of Loue, they may liue by thee. Grant this (O Father of mercie) to mee and all thy seruants, for thy sonnes sake, Iesus Christ our Lord and Sauiour, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:176864:59"/>
                     <head>A prayer for true loue.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Othing, O Lorde, can displease thee more, then want of loue, vvhere thou art loue. We are aboue all thinges bounde to loue thee, by whose loue wee liue: but yet none can loue thee but hee that loueth man; for these two be inseparate, to loue thee, and man in thee; thou hast commanded the loue of both, and yet without thy grace (who art loue) we cannot loue: giue me grace therefore, O Lord, to loue thee, and then to loue all men, hating onely their sinne: but especially to loue them that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:176864:59"/>loue thee, and in loue are like vnto thee. Guide me to loue my neighbour, as Ionathan did loue Dauid, euen as mine owne selfe. Keepe mee from hating of anie thing, but that Serpent that warres against the woman, and all her seed; for hee that loueth the Serpent, cannot loue thee, or thine; because the Serpent Satan hateth nothing more thē thee, &amp; those that be thine. And seeing that all mankinde came but of one man, let vs haue the grace to liue together as one, because wee came of one. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides this (O Lord) I see the loue of thy foes, how they loue one another, though it be in euill: if Saule die, his squire wil die. Let vs not bee slacke in true loue,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:176864:60"/>that so thy kingdome may bee promoted, and thy name maie in vs be Hallowed; thorough Iesus Christ our Lord and only redeemer, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for Hospitalitie.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, mankinde is so greatly multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and so manie are thy poore ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, and so little is their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe in most places, that dogs may fare better then thy poore Lazarus, in many a place. O Lord, we professe our selues to be the sonnes of Abraham, and our hope is at length to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into his bosome: but,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:176864:60"/>alas, our hearts and bowels are in most places so straite against the stranger, that a man canne hardly see the steppe of Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham. There was but one Lot in Sodome; and alas how fewe be the Lots, that now adaies do courteously intreat others: nay (alas) though the poore, be thy poore, and thou art poore in them; yet may they as soone in many places, get a checke, or a whippe, or a worse turne, then a morsell of bread: The rich gluttons of our time, are so rich in the contempt of the poore, indeed of thee, O Lord. Looke downe from heauen, and giue eare to the complaint of thy ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, though neuer so poore; yet bought by the deare death,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:176864:61"/>and purged in the pure bloud of thy sonne, as well as any other. Turne the hearts of the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, and open their hearts that they may see better to their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie then they haue done: strike them with some feares, that they may learne to feare thee, remembring that they were not made for themselues, but according to thy will (vnlesse they will incurre the danger of thy displeasure) to bee good to others: it is shame that the rich should liue, besides their liuings, to fill their owne purses, and to let thine goe naked in euerye place, and little regarded. Lay this shame before their eies that are rich, that they maie bee ashamed of their cruelties
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:176864:61"/>past, and learne for the time to come to be charitable. Elizeus found a Sunamite: but now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las what comforte is there in most places? Howe rare is the Gaius whom Iohn maie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend? O how many are they whome the example of Lidia may condemne? Fewe be our Aquilaes, &amp; Priscillaes. Where is Zacheus almost now adaies to be had? We haue few Tanners like to Simon; few women like to Martha; few Rebeccaes; few Labans; fewe gouernours like to Publius. Alas, how fewe be the Philemons of our time? O Lord, this is naught, amend it, or ende it; thy poore seruants craue it of thee, their groanes are great, they pant after thine
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:176864:62"/>ordinance: and therefore as all reformation is in thy power, so pitie thy poore, for Iesus Christs sake, to whom with thee and the holy Ghost, be all honour and glorie, now and for euer, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for the poore.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L states (O lord) depend vpon thy will, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, but for the good of thine, whatsoeuer their estate bee: giue me grace (O Lord) to rest vpon thy will, to be contented with thy pleasure, be it neuer so poore, assuring my selfe that I am thine, and thine Angels
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:176864:62"/>my seruantes, whether I liue or die, in more want then the dog of a Diues. Lazarus my brother foūd it: let me find the like fauor in thy good time, casting al my cares on thee, who carest for thy poore ones, that they maie be rich in thee, be they neuer so poore. And heere (O Lord) I praie not only for myselfe, but for all my poore brethren: giue them grace to be patient, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide such triall in their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And if it be thy will, soften the hard hearts of the rich, who haue not onely sufficient for themselues, but for thy poore seruaunts. Vouchsafe then (O Lord) this thy grace for the time to come, and for the time past, be thou mercifull to them, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:176864:63"/>them their vnkindnesse to vs their poore brethren, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to thee in vs, who in earth doe beare thy person. Graunt this (O Father of mercie) for Christes sake, our onely media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and aduocate, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for Grace to rebuke sinne in the wicked.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here the wicked (O God) cruelly destroy thēselues by sinne, whose wages is death, it is our duty to shew our care to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, in reprehending of them; it is a worke of mercy,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:176864:63"/>and becommech thy children, who art the Father of mercie: but alas, nowe adaies, where is this grace almost to be found? Lying, swearing, whoredome, hatred, all sinnes abounde: and yet almost where is he or she to be founde, that doth controwle it? Abraham checkt Abime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech; and so did Lot mildly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke the Sodomites; yea Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than found fault with his Father Saule, for his vniust pursute of Dauid. But (alas) now the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band may fall; but where is A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigail? nowe the people maie sinne; but where is Helias? now where is Nathan, that dare speake to Dauid? or a Daniel, to a Balthazer? Oh, where is he almost that soothes not, but is
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:176864:64"/>sharpe against, the sinnes of the wicked? Nay (alas) Aman found a flattering wife to hurt him; so did Achab to his losse, decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing prophets: Herode flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Iewes, and so doe men nowe adaies, not checke sinne, but soothe them in sinne, and praise them in euill, which is the next way to sende man to the diuell. O most miserable misery, that euer men, and such as run vnder the name of Christian men, should flatter themselues in sin, which is an euill as bad as the diuell, if not worse, because sinne made a good Angell a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. Giue mee (O Lord) better grace, to take sinne for my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie and deadlie foe, to repent it, to denie it, to condemne it in
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:176864:64"/>my selfe and others; that it may neuer come in condemnation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst me: and turne their harts to wisedome, that make no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of thy will, but rather of sin, and care for nothing more then howe they may fulfill the course of their sinne. O Lord, stop them in their euill course, as thou diddest stoppe Paul, when he was a Saul, and the son that once was prodigall, and the theefe, who yet vpon the Crosse became thy true and bold Saint dying for sinne, and yet stoutlie rebuking sinne, and was saued from sinne, by thine onely son made sinne to make him, and al such thy righteousnesse in him. Grant this (O Father of mercy in thy Sonne Iesus Christ, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="112" facs="tcp:176864:65"/>whom alone thou art appeased, and well pleased with thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants: to whom with thee, and the holy Ghost, three persons, and one God eternall, bee all glory ascribed, for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for the grace of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passion in anie time of trouble.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L Christians are chic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, and their Hen, they are Lambes, and their shepheard, they are branches, and their vine, they are members of one body, and their head is one, thy sweet sonne alone: so that not onely,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:176864:65"/>they are bounde by nature, but grace to beare one anothers burthen in compassion, counsel, and other comforts. But (alas) now adaies, if Lot bee captiue, where is the Abraham almost that striues to redeeme him? Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph was in danger of life, but yet he found a Ruben: Iezabell did persecute the prophets, and yet they found an Abdias: It made Nehemias many daies to weepe, to heare the miserable state of Ierusalem. When Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherib raigned, and hated the children of Israel, yet found they a comforting Tobias; who fed the hungry, cloathed the naked, and buried the dead, O that we had such Abrahams, and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens now a daies: Oh that wee
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:176864:66"/>had Iobes in this day of pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wherein the needy crie for succour. O Lorde giue vs grace to respect, not onely our selues, but our brothers case; yea, and not onely our brother in grace, but in nature: for the bowels of Christian compassion ought to be general. Samuel (O Lord) did mourne for Saule, and Dauid for Absolon, and the Prophet Esay for Babilon: Paul greeued for the Athenians, and Christ himselfe wept for the Iewes. Guide mee (O Lorde) with the same spirit of loue towardes all, to weepe with thy Saintes wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, &amp; to pity thē, that no waie pittie themselues; but wilfully runne into the very iawes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and mouth of hell, which is
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:176864:66"/>large, and alwaies gaping to swallow vp the wicked. O lord, if it be thy will, call them from themselues to thee; soften their heartes, that they may yeeld to thy will, and bee saued by thy good will; through Iesus Christ our onely Sauiour, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for grace, not to bee offended at the offences of the wicked.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is, O Lord, a thing to be pittied, that thy seruantes cannot dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their duties to thee in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny measure, either in iudging themselues, or in correcting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for their sinnes; but the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:176864:67"/>wicked are stra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ghtwaies offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with them. For this cause Asa King of Iuda could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide Hanani: in this point Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charias the son of Ioiada found a Ioas to commaund him to bee stoned: in fauour of Bell, that false God, the Lyons Denne was thought a place good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for Daniel: nay in this respect the Galileans prooued fooles, they counted Paul their enemie. Trueth it is, that trueth coulde neuer yet finde good li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the worlde, neither can it, because the diuell that Father of lies, is God of the world. Nay (alas) if man finde iust fault with his owne sins, and do reclaime himselfe, and meddle not with others, (whereunto yet charitie
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:176864:67"/>bindeth euery Christian,) what falleth out but contempt of such a person? So that now nothing is more common, then to set naught by the groate that hath beene lost, and yet is found: to flout the sonne, that of a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall is become a thriftie sonne. O world full of sinne, nothing is more vsuall, then to mocke the man that is become of a decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, simple; of a foole, discreet; of an vsurer, free; of a wanton, chast; of a hater, a louer; of a swearer, a praiser of Gods holie Name. It is a common thing, to scorne the man that becomes of a sinner a Saint; the vvicked make such a one their laughing stocke, because hee doth by his amendment condemne their
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:176864:68"/>wicked liues, which best liketh them: O miserable blindnes! O Lord, open their eies, that they may iudge their selues, and iudge better of them, who iudge themselues, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne their owne sinnes. And if it bee so, that I liue among them, who are scorners of thee, and thy seruants, Lord giue thy grace, that I be no way discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged in my christian course, by such diuelish contempt: but that I may fight out my fight, finish my course, and keepe the faith, and by faith keepe my selfe purely religious, against all of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences whatsoeuer. Grāt this (O Father) for Iesus Christes sake, our only mediatour and aduo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:176864:68"/>
                     <head>A prayer against lying.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is nothing more common a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs (O Lord) thē to professe thy seruice, who art the God of truth, and yet in our liues to be lying seruants, by disobeying thee, and obeying the father of lies. It cannot be (O Lord) but a grieuous thing to lie, because that all lies be of the Diuel, who was the first lier that euer was: nay, alas, it is a dangerous thing to lie. For what got Adam and Eue by beleeuing a lie, and the lier? O, what shall become of them, that do not only beleeue,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:176864:69"/>but tell lies? This was the sinne of Pharao, the sinne of Anani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as; the sinne of Aman against Mardocheus; the sinne of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and people against Ieremie the Prophet; the sinne of the Iewes against Steuen, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our Sauiour, the Saint of all Saints: But, alas, what did these wicked persons, or others at any time get by their lying? Ananias got a suddaine death: Lord, saue me from it, and from lying the cause. Haman got at last a gibbet: Lord preserue me, stop my heart, and mouth, that I doe not lie: King Pharao at lēgth was drowned with others, and numbers haue felt in this world thy heauie hand for this sinne. Whereby thou hast made
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:176864:69"/>it knowne to all the world, that as thou art truth it selfe, so thou canst not abide a lie: nay to feare vs from this sinne, if tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall punishmentes will not moue men, thou hast denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the plagues of hell against the lier, which might be suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, to worke in vs hatred of all lying, if any thing might serue. But yet, alas, all is nothing to whole multitudes, they waie not either thy temporal, or eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall punishing of this sinne. Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was neuer so common If it be thy will (O Lord) take from men the spirit of lies, and indue them with the spirite of truth, both by word, and worke, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the oath of baptisme, to glorifie thee: And giue me
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:176864:70"/>that strength of thy spirit, that I may keepe my mouth from ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; but especially (O Lord) let me not be a lier in life. I haue promised to serue thee, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am a lier, an abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble lier, if I doe not serue thee: and yet without thee I cannot serue thee, except thy grace do make me able. Able me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (O Lord) to serue thee, for Iesus Christes sake; to whom with thee, and thy spirite be all honour, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:176864:70"/>
                     <head>A prayer against treason.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL power is of thee (O Lord) to whome power belongeth: by thee it is, that Kings doe raigne; thou art the God, that hast said, they are Gods: their estate in thee is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto vs, for they are thy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters: nay, thou hast com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all men to honour and obey them; not only forfeare, but for conscience sake: but yet, alas, many men, in all ages haue prooued so miferable, as not onely by Doctrine to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, but by practise to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw this thine ordinance. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:176864:71"/>found an Absalon, Zachari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the King of Israell found a Shallum, Senacherib was smit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by his two Sonnes in the Temple, as he was praying: O vnnaturall! O Diuelish trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son! nay, alas, as it was of old, so is it nowe, that none can liue lesse secure then the Magistrate, if Amasa might feare the kisse of Ioab, when but nowe the wicked are in league, if they might compasse a Nehemias it is their desire. But no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell though the wicked doe so spite thine ordinance, seeing thine owne, and onely sonne, could not bee free from Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and the seruaunt is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his Maister. Yet (O Lord) if it be thy pleasure, make soft
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:176864:71"/>the hearts of such persons, who any waie seeke to stand with the Diuell, and withstand thy Gods vpon earth. Especiallie (O Lorde) cast thy fauourable eie vppon England: long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue our gratious Princesse E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizabeth, and all her faithfull seruants from the treacherie of forrainer, or priuie, or dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sticall foe whatsoeuer; as thou hast done, so doe still, that thy Gospell maie haue free course, the Diuell may be foyled of his purposes, that we may still be comforted, and thou haue the glorie; through Iesus Christ our Lord, and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:176864:72"/>
                     <head>A prayer necessary for this our time.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, who hast al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way beene won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful in thy saints; as carefull of them, as any Hen could be of her chickens, or any man of the Apple of his eie, or Mother of the fruite of her wombe: worke the wonder of thy mercy vppon vs. True it is (O Lord) that the latter times, and therefore the sinfull times, are come vppon vs; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore such times, as do not onely deserue, but vppon desert crie out, for an end of our time: O Lord, therefore looke not vpon
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:176864:72"/>our sinnes, but turne thy face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from them, and behold vs in the face of thy sonne; for his sake (O Lord) forgiue vs. The bloude of Abell crieth for ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, but let thy sonnes blood cry for vs in thine eares, not ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, but mercy: And for the time to come giue vs grace to liue better, then as yet wee haue doone, to lead that life that beseemeth thy gospell. And where thy gospell hath had free course among vs these manie yeares; giue vs thankefull harts to thee, and defende the free course of the same against all such as spite the glory of thy name; for nowe the diuels time groweth short, and therefore now hee threatens by his Pope
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:176864:73"/>and Spaniarde a shorte and sharpe time, euen within three daies, to set their bloudy feet in England. But the cause is thine owne (O Lorde) and thou hast these manie yeares beene the onely patrone of it, and at this time their wild fire balles thou hast disclosed. Arise therefore (O God) still, and maintaine thy owne cause; thou wast able to saue Noe from the floud, Lot from Sodome, Daniel from the Lyon, Paul from Nero, and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Chaine: yea, at thy Almighty will, Holofernes was nothing to a Iudith, nor Goliah to a Dauid, nor Herode to a worme, nor Pharao to a frog. O Lorde, thou art but one, and there is no shadow of change in
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:176864:73"/>thee: thou art euerlastingly and equally strong; strengthen vs therefore (O Lorde) shewe thy might in our weaknes, the more weake we are, the more shal be the glory of thy power in our defence. Make thy fooles suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to confound the wife, and thy weake ones able for them that crake of their might. Pope and Spaniarde count vs vile things, as nothing to them: they haue said it in their heartes, and sworne it with their mouthes, that there is no God to saue vs from them. O Lord, thou sittest and seest all, laugh them to scorne: thou madest of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible Armadoes, no better then a Babel. O Lord, stil make good thy power against those
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:176864:74"/>proude diuels, who hauing felt the hand of thy power; yet wil not acknowledge thee: they are but chaffe to thee: O God, it is an easie thing for thee to featter them: make thy droppe suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the floud, let not thy lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle flocke feare, but be of good cheere in thee. Saue, O Lord, our gracious Queene, long, and long maintaine her: guide, O Lord, her honourable councell, in all their consultations. Blesse the Ministerie of thy word, and giue vs religious and pitifull ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates. Haue mercy vpon all the Commons of this Realme; giue vs all tender heartes, with Peters eies to lament our sinnes: teach vs to proue our religion by good works, in all our works
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:176864:74"/>to depend on thee; to cast our cares on thee; so canst thou not but care for vs; and if thou care for vs, we care for no more. O Lord, therefore in thee giue vs grace to put our trust, that wee may not be confounded. Grant this, O Father of mercy, for thy sonnes sake, to whom with thee and the holy Ghost, be al praise and glory now and euer, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <p>ALmightie and mercifull Father, we humblie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful vnto vs, forgiue vs our sins, and for thine owne sake, spare vs good Lord. O Lord, be thou
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:176864:75"/>our buckler, and shield: teach our hands to warre, and our fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to fight, that we maie doe valiant thinges in thy name, to thy glorie, and our comfort. And now especially (O sweete God) looke downe from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vpon vs, for now the Diuell is angrie, and hungrie to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure vs, he is a Serpent and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till Lyon, and mightily doth he attempt our desolation: and therefore he threatens by Land, and Sea, and practizeth euerie waie to compasse vs. He hath said within himselfe, that hee will be at out heeles by Land, and in the face of death by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter against vs. But sweete God though Pharao were at our heeles, and the waters in our
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:176864:75"/>face, and death gaping vppon vs; yet art thou that mightie God, that art able to close the nouth of death, if it be thy will the waters giue place, Israell doth safely passe, and Pharao drownes; thou conquerest him that maketh full account of a conquest: O Lord in like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner deale with vs: where the Pharaoes of Rome, and Spaine doe reckon of our finall decay, if it be thy good mercie stoppe their attempt; if not, yet Lord stoppe their intent, and giue not thy enemies that euent, that may make them proude: but if they pursue vs, pursue them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: O God, let them drinke of Pharaoes cuppe, that offer to thy Israell so bitter a cuppe.
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:176864:76"/>Giue long breath to our grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Queene, and giue her grace aboue all things to serue thee, and knit the harts of all her sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, first to serue thee; and next to serue her faithfully in thee. Fauour all, O Lorde, that fauour her cause, or rather thine owne cause; defende her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, defend her religion, thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. O God defend all that fight for thy trueth vnder her Banners, whether they bee for her by land or sea; follow them with thy power: guide them, O Lord, in this seruice, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie shall not be ours, but thine: and therefore for thine owne sake heare vs: bee thou their counseller and fortresse, a wall of fence to them, and al that are
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:176864:76"/>with them. This, at this time, we (O Lord) doe craue of thee, in whom resteth our whole and onely comfort, for without thee all wisedome is follie, and all might is infirmitie; but in thee the verie sight of a hand maie dazell a Balthazer: Goliahs beame is nothing to a sling stone, no nor many weapons to an Affes lawbone: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O Lord our God, we will sitte vnder thy shadowe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching thee to couer with thy winges all such, as by Land or Sea doe fight in the quarrell, and cause of thy sonne. Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it because thou hearest onely such as beleeue, and none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, but such as doe not onely professe, but in godly life ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:176864:77"/>true religion: Therefore (sweet God) giue vs repenting and beleeuing hearts, and giue vs grace to liue according to thy worde; that so wee maie praie, and praying bee heard, and being heard may still tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph against all the fiery darts of Sathan to our comfort, and thy glory, through Iesus Christ our Lord; to whom with thee and the holy ghost, three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and one God, be all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and praise, world without end, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <p>O Lord God, king almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, all thinges are in thy power; if thou hast ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:176864:77"/>to saue England, there is no man that can withstande thee: for thou hast made hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, and all the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous things vnder heauen: thou art Lord of all things, and there is no man that can resist thee, which art the Lord. O Lorde, shew thy power, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>e our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and be mercifull to thy por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; rebuke the tempest, and command vs a calme, forgiue vs all our sins, and saue vs from that proude Haman of Rome, who spites to see Mardocheus in peace, because hee will not prefer the honour of a man, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue thy glory, and wil not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship but thee onely his Lorde. Hereuppon it is (O Lorde) that they imagine howe to bring vs
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:176864:78"/>to naught, to destroy thine inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, to shut the mouthes of them that praise thee: yea, and if they coulde in one day with violence thrust vs downe into hell, to the intent that their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires might be without contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction or trouble. Thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est this (O Lord) who knowest all thinges, and therefore haue mercy vppon vs thy people: turne the threats of the time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to peace, that wee may liue and praise thy name. Let the light and the Sun rise vp, let the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee exalted, and the glorious be deuoured. Grant this, O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for Iesus Christes sake A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:176864:78"/>
                     <head>A prayer against heresie and Schisme.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, as thy onely sonnes coate was wouen, and without seame or diuision; so ought all thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants to bee one, and knit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one faith, in one hope, in thee one, and their onely God: but yet alas, the diuell is busie to make rentes of thy seamelesse coate, and by heresie &amp; schisme to ouerthrow the profession of thy name. And to that purpose knowing his time to bee short, he hath plaied his spitefull part in these latter times, troubling both state and church with sore
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:176864:79"/>separations. O Lord, heale these wounds; if it be thy will, giue vs all thy grace to be of one mind; and if that be not thy will, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to cut them off that do disquiet other Churches, and this thy Church of England: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptistes, Barowistes, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistes, Chamishe, Martinistes, the familie of loue, which no way loueth thee, Heretikes, Schismatiques, al Epicures and Atheists. O Lorde, either of thy mercy conuert, or in thy iustice speedily confound them, so shall thy little drop be safe against all the water flouds of Sathan. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I cannot but confesse and lament many imperfections that be among vs: O Lord, open our eies to see them, our heartes
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:176864:79"/>to acknowledge them cal them home againe that bee scandali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by them; and giue mee grace no way to separate my selfe from thy Church for anie frailty: but rather (good Lorde) I beseech thee, to confirme me in thee, against all offences; to redresse in thy good time, what thou knowest to bee amisse, to stop the malicious pennes of all them that are giuen to penne some truthes; but yet to the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite of many manifest lies, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing vppon the blemishes of men, against the purenes, yea, and truenes of thy Church a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong vs. O Lord, shew this thy mercy vpon this thy Church of England, and giue vs thankfull hearts to thee, for the course of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:176864:80"/>the Gospell, least by vnthankful diuision we loose it, and all bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sings with it. Grant this (O fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercy) for Iesus Christes sake, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A prayer for grace, to carie a true reuerence towardes Gods word.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ithout the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thee (O Lord) it is vnpos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible for any man to be saued: and how shall a man know thy will, but by thy word? Which word thou thy selfe diddest first vouchsafe to write in wans hart, and afterwards with thine own
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:176864:80"/>finger, in Tables of stone: so that if I either care for my selfe, or thy reuerence, I must reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence thy word My sweet lord, thy onely sonne is my onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, in whome thou art wholy delighted, he himselfe deliuered thy word, and afterwardes sent his Disciples to declare the same to the world: yea, and by thine owne worde, wee ought to reuerence thy worde from their mouthes, as though it were from thy owne; for hee that heareth them, heareth thee. Manie other arguments (O Lord) there are, which ought to perswade men to carie a due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of thy word: but yet (alas) this is the miserie of our misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble time, wee care for nothing
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:176864:81"/>lesse then thy worde. The lier contemneth thy worde, the swearer, the adulterer, the vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, because thy worde con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth their lying, whoring, swearing, vsurie, and all the sins of the wicked: Nay, alas, such is the miscrie of men nowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daies, that they will vpon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of their sinnes, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse thy Gospell, condemne thy Gospell, and also speake most vilely of it. O Lorde, saue me from such temptations, and giue them the spirite of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that haue yeelded to such grosse illusions: for thy worde dependeth not vppon man, but it is to be taken, as it is indeede, for thy worde who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer doeth vtter it: truth is
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:176864:81"/>truth, though Cayphas doe prophecie; and the father of lies, doeth not alwaies lie; though he call my Sauiour thy sonne, I must beleeue it, because thy worde is so, though not because hee speaketh so. O Lorde, therefore giue me grace to carrie a due regarde of thy worde; though Iudas doe preach it, giue mee grace to waie not who speakes, but what is spoken. Grant this, O Father of mercie, for Iesus Christs sake, our onely me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, and aduocate, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:176864:82"/>
                     <head>A prayer to God for them, that are troubled in minde.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lorde God, thou Father of mercie, be mercifull vnto me, and looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me thy poore creature heere distressed. O Lord, the Diuell is a malicious and mercilesse ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, he spiteth all thy creatures, but especially thy seruants, and all such as haue desire to please thee, because he is contrarie to thee: yet (O Lord) the Diuell can doe nothing, but as thou shalt please to suffer him, and and oftentimes it pleaseth thee, not of thy wrath, but for trials
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:176864:82"/>sake: and therefore in thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to giue him leaue, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to spoile Iob of his goods, but of his bodies health; yet reseruing his soule safe vnto thy selfe. O sweet God, therefore thy sweete will be done, I thy poore seruaunt haue deserued greater trouble then this, and by thy will it is, that Iob was, and I am troubled; O Lorde, therefore I beseech thee, be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me a gratious God; if it bee thy pleasure, restore me to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect strength, and vse of my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die: if not, yet (O Lorde) haue pitie vpon my poore soule. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not (O Lord) my sins, marke not what I haue done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse, enter not into iudgement with mee, but remember thy
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:176864:83"/>sweete, and deerely beloued: remember his bodies tearing, and his soules suffering for me, and stoppe thine eares against the crie of mine offences, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen them to the cries of thy son: hearken (O Lord) to the crie of his bloud, his head did bleed, let that crie; his hands did bleed, let them crie; his side was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: his head did bleed (O lord) al; al his bodie was in a sweat, &amp; what was that sweat but like drops of bloud trickling downe to the ground? O Lorde, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to those manifolde cries of his precious bloud, running from all partes of his body, and wash me cleane from sin there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: but especially (O Lord) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his sweet soule, heauie
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:176864:83"/>euen vnto the death, to saue me from death, by reason of sin my due. O remember howe thou hast punished all the sinnes of al thy Seruants in him, and for his sake, being made sinne, to saue them all from sinne. With them I desire thee to respect mee one of thy distressed creatures, labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for, and only comming vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee for ease. The woman of Canaan had a daughter, and she was miserably vexed with a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell; her mother was a dog, and not worthy of a crumme that might fall from thy childrens ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: yet (O God) shee cried for mercy, and founde mercy at length. O Lord, bee the same God of mercy to me, who here pray for my selfe, not in mine
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:176864:84"/>owne name, but in the name of thy Sonne, who became the Sonne of Dauid. As hee was (O Lorde) vnto the woman of Canaan and her daughter, so be thou to mee in him, an ease in trouble, the God of my saluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, against all the temptations of Sathan whatsoeuer. O Lord, haue care of mee, and loue mee in Christ thy beloued, who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me to the death, to saue me from death by his death, being life. Good Lord, I beseech thee for thy mercies sake, be thus mercifull vnto me, forgiue mee all my sinnes, and treade Sathan vnder my feete shortly. In the name of Iesus Christ. O Lord, graunt this, I beseech thee, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="151" facs="tcp:176864:84"/>
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <p>FAther of mercy, without thee I am miserable, and better nothing, then anie thing; O pitie thy creature, and do not forsake mee, seeke him that is a stranger, sweepe for me (O Lord) without thee a lost groate, represse the rage of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than; thou canst do it (O Lorde) I beseech thee, in thy sweete Sonne to be willing. Giue me strength of grace to withstand, and so to shame the diuell; as Iob did by his patience rest him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe onely in thee, so let me pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse my soule in patience. I know (O Lord) that thing can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be lost that is committed to
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:176864:85"/>thy hands: and therfore as thou giuest mee grace to do, so do I commit my body and soule into thine hands: Thou hast made &amp; thy deare &amp; onely Sonne hath bought me, and therefore in thy own son take me forthine own, and let thy right hand be my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and comfort, against all discomfort whatsoeuer. Giue me the assistance of thy Spirite, that I may bee sorie for my sins, that I by them haue displeased thee anie way. O Lorde giue mee grace to displease my selfe in all things, wherein I haue not pleased thee, that so by displea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing my selfe thorough thy good spirite, I may please thee. Grant this, O Father of mercie, for Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christes sake, in whome
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:176864:85"/>now and euer, I commend my selfe vnto thee, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A Prayer for them that are visited with sicknes.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> GOD of health, I thy sicke seruant, haue none in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or earth, that can comfort me besides thee: to thee nothing is vnpossible, and therefore if thou wilt, thou canst make me whole: thy will be doone, O lord, whether it please thee to restore me to my former strength, or else to take me to thy mercy: thou knowest what is best for me, and I know that thou workest all good things, to
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:176864:86"/>their good that loue thee. Yea, O Lord, by this thy Fatherly correction thou prouest thy loue towards me, for thereby thou doest humble me, and make me to remember my sinnes, and teachest me to runne for my ease vnto thee, which is the next way to be strong in weakenes, merry in heauines, cheerefull in distresse, to be in life, when wee are in death, it is heauen to the man that is in hel, and extreame affliction: and therefore in this thy chastening of me, I find thy loue assured to mee; thou tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chest mee to come vnto thee, being laden with the weight of sinne and sicknesse, that I may find some ease in thee. O Lord, if it be thy pleasure come and
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:176864:86"/>ease me quickly: assist me with the spirite of patience, let thy grace make me strong against al temptations whatsoeuer: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue me all my sinnes, and for thy deare sonnes sake, be thou mercifull vnto mee. I beleeue that he suffered sufficiently, and fully to saue me from Sathan: O Lord, increase this my faith, and according to my faith, so let me be heard: Thou art a grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, and thine eares are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies open to the grieued and wearie person, that pants after thy comforts: and therefore as I thirst after thee, and none but thee, so manifest thy grace vpon me: be thou my comforter, my fortresse, and rocke of defence; let thy deare sonnes bloudie
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:176864:87"/>death stand before me and thy iustice, and speake peace to my conscience, that whether I liue or die, I maie liue to die, and die to liue, assured of eternall life in the death of Christ, whom I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue by death, to be my onely life: Grant this O father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, for Iesus Christes sake, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Another.</head>
                     <p>DEath, O Lord, is the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of sin; and therefore, O Lord, I confesse, that I am worthy to die: but yet sweet God, in the death of thy sonne, whom thou didest punish suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently for my sinne, be thou
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:176864:87"/>mercifull vnto mee, to for giue me my sinnes, and turne death to mine aduantage in him, that it maie be a sweete sleepe, and no death vnto me; dying not to die, but by death to come to thee, that I maie liue with thee euerlastingly. This (O Lord) is all my desire; O let my crie come vnto thee, giue me grace whensoeuer I leaue this wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched life, to make a blessed end, that I maie depart in peace in Christ thy son, mine only peace, and contentation: his birth, his life, his death, his resurrection, all that he is, and is his, by faith, O Lord, I count it mine owne, as my sinnes were his, and lai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vpon him who neuer knew sin, and yet was made sinne, that I
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:176864:88"/>might be thy righteousnesse in him. O Lord, increase this faith in mee, and according to this faith which is thy worke, doe thou respect me, for in my selfe I haue no cause or colour of comfort but onely in thy sonne, in whom I know thee to be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well pleased. O sweet Christ in him thy beloued, loue me, and be wel pleased towards me thy sicke, and weake creature: God be merciful to me a sinner: Iesus receiue my spirit: Father into thy handes I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my Spirit, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="159" facs="tcp:176864:88"/>
                     <head>A prayer needefull for all the people of this Land.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HY Name (O Lord) is the Lord of hostes; and therfore they are fooles, that doe prouoke thee to anger; and yet, alas, such fooles we haue beene, and thou (O God) knowest our follies: O Lord, impute them not vnto vs, but haue mercie vpon vs: giue vs soft heartes, broken hearts; make vs wearie with the weight of our sinnes, that wee maie learne to flie to thee for succour. O Lorde, if thou wouldest, thou mightest
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:176864:89"/>bring vs to hell, we haue deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued no better a lodge then Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas did: but we know that thou art a gratious God, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, slow to anger, and of great kindnesse. Ionas could pitie a small thing, and bee angrie for the withering of a gourde, <hi>Ion.</hi> 3. which yet he neither labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red nor made to grow; and wilt not thou (O Lord) be merciful to the people of England? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed (O Lord) Ionas hath been among vs, and hath cried yet 40. daies; nay not onely daies, but yeeres: and yet we are not like to the Niniuites, that yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not onely vpon 40. yeeres, but daies. O Lord, giue vs bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hearts for the time to come, giue vs grace to put on sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:176864:89"/>to cry mightily vnto thee: Assist vs so with thy spirite, that euery man may turne from his euill way, and from the vilenes that is in their hands. Thou spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redst Niniuie that great Citie, and madest to Ionas this merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full question and checke; why he should be angry for the losse of a gourde? and vvhy thou shouldest not spare Niniuie that great citie, wherein there were sixscore thousand persons, that could not discern between their right hand, and their left hand, and also many cattell? O Lord, if thou be so mercifull to beasts, be mercifull to vs; let thy loue, and the light of thy counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce bee shewed vppon vs: breake vp our fallowe grounde,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:176864:90"/>and sowe therein the seede of righteousnes: where the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest is great, and the surges of the Sea, O Lord, if it bee thy will, to send a calme: giue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Ionas grace to repent, and turne to thee, lest our shippe be troubled for his sake, and hee himselfe at length deuoured: or if it be thy will for our sinnes, to follow vs; yet (Lord) giue vs grace, when we are in hell, to crie vpon thee, and send vs some Whale to restore vs, if thou send one to swallow vs; thou art al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and canst doe it; the glory shall be thine. Grant this (O Father of mercy) for Iesus Christes sake, our only mediator and aduocate, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <pb n="163" facs="tcp:176864:90"/>
                     <head>A Prayer for her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Prince of this world (O Lord) is not able without thy leaue to touch any creature of thine, though he bee malicious, mercilesse, and mighty; yet his might is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, if it please thee to restraine him of his will: O Lord, wee know this thy strength, and that thy only strength is sufficient a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him. We beseech thee therefore to pardon our sinnes, we acknowledge them, and hartily lament them, we abhor them, O Lord; and therefore (O Lord) abhor not thou vs, for
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:176864:91"/>thy names sake, cast not away the throne of thy glory. <hi>Ier. 14.20.21.</hi> Our trust is not in any of the Gentiles vanities, but onely in thee: and therefore hold thy mercifull hand towards vs (O Lord) be not weary of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, <hi>Ier. 15.6.</hi> though thou presently threat the plagues: yet giue vs new hearts, that thou maiest repent and spare vs. Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially (O Lord) be fauourable to thy seruaunt Elizabeth, our most gracious soueraigne, come against her enemies, as against thornes solden one in another: destroy them with the breath of thy mouth, if thy good will be not to turne their hearts, to fauour thy name and vs, that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the same. Saue her (O lord)
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:176864:91"/>and all her people committed to her charge, from the foules of the Heauen, and beasts of the Land, and fishes of the Sea, that they do not deuoure or destroy them: keepe from vs the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring dogge, and slaying sword O Lord, remember thy olde mercies, and be the same God of mercy still vnto vs: write our mercifull Princesse in thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull hand, and let her be as the apple of thine eie vnto thee, and send thine angell to pitch his tent aboue her, and all thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full seruants, that serue for hir a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny where in all the world, to the comfort of thine, to the shame of them that spurne against thee and thy secret ones. Grant this (O Father) for Iesus Christes
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:176864:92"/>sake, our onely Mediatour and Aduocate, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A Prayer for faire weather at anie time, aswell for committing fruits to the earth, as for there ceiuing of them and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blessings.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee to giue vs greeued hearts, and sorrovving Soules; for our sins are many and mighty, and wee know that thou art a holy God and iust: and yet, alas, lying, swearing, whoredome, malice, vsury, pride; alas, what sin is it that aboundeth not in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:176864:92"/>O Lord, these be great sinnes in the heathen that know thee not: howe much more greeuous in vs who haue profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed thy knowledge, and haue vowed obedience to thy Holy name. And therefore seeing we serue thee not accordingly, we cannot but most highly dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>please thee: of which thy iust displeasure, thou hast shewed vs of late yeares especially, sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry and memorable tokens. We haue beene visited with pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilence almost generall, and threat of Sword: It is not long since, O Lord, that our Haruest was short, and Corne so scant, that thereupon there came such want among vs thy people, as neuer was knowne in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:176864:93"/>of man now liuing: And thou seest, O GOD, that the most are neuer the better, or in life amended thereby: the deare yeere is forgotten by the most, wished againe by many: the rich of England thinke Corne too cheape, the poore bee not thankefull for the plenty; all states for the greatest part, are giuen to riote and vvaste, as though there could not grow a new want. It is true, O Lord, and thou seest it; and therefore now thou doest smite vs againe with vnseasonable weather, so that wee cannot commit our Corne to the earth (or receiue thy blessings from the earth) in due season. O Lord, bee merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto vs, and giue vs grace to
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:176864:93"/>iudge our selues, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne our owne sinnes, which are the cause of sickenes, pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, persecution, and all calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Giue the proude of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land grace to remember, they are but dust; the couetous, that they came into this worlde na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and shall cary nothing but sinne to condemne them, vnles they repent. Giue the lyer grace to speake trueth, the swearer to feare thee; giue al wantons the grace of Mary Magdalen, to weepe; giue the extortioners of the land, the gift of Zacheus, to make restitution; and all thy people, O Lorde, blesse them with true contrite hearts, that so we may feare thee, and in feare serue thee; and in our seruing of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:176864:94"/>thee, seeke thee first: so shall wee bee sure to sow and reape, to begin and ende, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, till wee come to a bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed end, which in thee shall last in Heauen, and neuer haue end. Graunt this, O Lorde, for Iesus Christes sake, our onely Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour and Aduocate, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>Another Prayer after recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the fruites of the earth, with a complaint of the time.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> LORD God, as all thinges are thine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause thou hast made them, and all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ought to be thy seruants,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:176864:94"/>because they are thine: yet, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, where all other creatures are readie to do thy will and serue thee, which art the maker, (fierce to punish the wicked, but easie to doe good to such as put their trust in thee:) such is our misery, that wee eyther know not, or weigh not of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. O Lord, when did not the Heauens declare thy Glory? when did the earth refuse to be thy footestoole? At thy worde the Sea swelles not, the winde blowes not, the funne steps not; yea, the Sunne runs not: the earth doth open to swallow, the water is firme to beare vp a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy body: if Peter doubt, hee may begin to finke; til he doubt he may walke vpon the water.
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:176864:95"/>At thy will, O Lord, Snow and yce will abide the fire, fire will burne in the haile, and sparkle in the raine. What creature is it, O Lord, that may not come in condemnation, not onely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Iewes, Turks, Heathens, and Infidels; but against such as run vnder the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians: amongst whome there is now adaies to bee found little faith, much falsenesse: much doubling, little loue without dissembling; much pride, small humilitie; great couetousnesse, little pitie. The most liue, but without repentance, as though they were in hope of Heauen without repentance; as though there were no God, because no iust God, who cannot bee iust,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:176864:95"/>vnles he reward euery man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his deedes. O Lord, in respect of our manifold and greeuous sinnes, thou hast smit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vs sundry waies, that wee may learne to remember our selues, what we are; and thee, what a iust God thou art: vnles we repent and amend our liues. The very beastes of the fielde haue mourned for want of grasse and water: thou didst put vs in feare of a short and vnseasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haruest: O lord, spare thy poore creature, fill with thy blessing euery liuing thing: send vs our daily bread, and make vs thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for thy goodnesse: it is by thee, that our haruest is so well gotten in. Graunt vs, O good God, a seasonable time to sow,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:176864:96"/>and true sorrow of heart for our sinnes, that in thy good time we may reape againe. And if it be thy wil to punish vs, yet (O lord) chide but for a time; beate vs with a fatherly rod, and be not angrie with vs foreuer. Graunt this O Father for thy sons sake, our sweete Sauiour, to whome with thee and the holy ghost be all honor and praise, both now and euer, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A speciall prayer for her Maie sties royall person, and the good estate of England.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, thou art that only light, in whom there is no darknes at all: thou art all eie and seest all: there is
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:176864:96"/>nothing hid from thee, but all things are naked to thine eies, with whom wee haue to doe. Nothing can bee attempted or intended, which thou knowest not, who knowest what is in man. And, as thy knowledge comprehends it, so thy power is sufficient to effect attempts, or to preuent all wicked intents. But yet (O Lord) we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued, not onely danger of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but damnation of soules: our sins are many, mightie, and the mightier to craue and crie out for iustice, because we haue not of so long time made better vse of thy manifold, manifest, marueilous, and therefore me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable fauours; wherby thou hast blessed vs aboue all other
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:176864:97"/>countries round about vs. We haue not beene thankefull to thee for our gracious Princesse, nor for our long and yet conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ioy by her gracious raigne. The most loathe Manna, they lust for the fleshpots of Egypt: thy word (O God) in wordes is truly and thoroughly protested; but thy word looseth grace by the gracelesse and ingratefull life of the most. For faith is growen scant, loue is frozen, sin aboundeth: Lots family in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land is little, but Lots griefe is not little to see it so little. Many haue faith in lips, how fewe in in life? Our Churches are open, how few come to pray? howe colde is deuotion? What daies are for the most part and by the
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:176864:97"/>most more prophaned, thē those daies that be appointed for thy seruice, O God? We haue rents and schisme, many professe he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie: nay, alas, insteed of super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious papisme or holy prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>station against heresie, schisme, and other sinne; what numbers professe with mouth or at least by vnchristian life, the Diuels high seruice, no better then A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theisme? O Lord, howe shall I complaine? England is full of drosse, our siluer is little: what multitudes fauour sinne? How few are zealous to stand in the gappe by true repentance and praiers against sin, which threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens on all sides (and without speedy repentance) a speedie and wofull end? O sweet God,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:176864:98"/>giue vs new harts, that we may serue thee in newnes of life: let the old man die, that the newe man may liue, and waxe strong in life. Blesse vs all, that we may be truely sory for our sinnes, and so preuent all feared and deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued sorrowes. Cut off, O lord, all Hereticall, Schismatical, and factious spirites, if it be not thy good will to sosten their hearts, that they may renounce their damnable &amp; dangerous course. Plant in them, if thy goodnesse bee such towardes them, true feare and honour of thy name, that they and we may worship thee (who art loue) in faith and loue, without rent or dislike of hearts whatsoeuer; that so we may ioine at home together a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:176864:98"/>forren force or foe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer, to the good of thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, comfort of thy people, and praise of thine alone praise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy name. Otherwise in iudgment make an end of them all, that shall attempt or intend with settled and resolute hearts, to worke their owne hearts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire by treason, rebellion or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction whatsoeuer, to the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of this land, to the griefe of all faithfull hearts, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfort of our gracious Queen; who for her gracious cares ouer vs frō time to time, to the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold perill of her roiall person, for the maintenance of Christs true religion and vertue against Caiphas and Cain, should bee absurdly rewarded with irreli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:176864:99"/>and factious course to her owne disquiet and the danger of all. O Lord God, thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est her gracious heart how desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous she is to haue thy religion defended and continued with peace, to the good of our soules: preuent the Diuels malice, who knoweth that a kingdome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided cannot stand; and blesse her roiall person and godly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, diuide and scatter them, that lust to be diuided. Blesse her Maiestie with long breath, that wee maye long breathe peaceable breath by her breath, and giue vs all zealous hearts to pray for the peace of England: Be the God of peace vnto vs, &amp; treade Sathan vnder our feete shortly. Grant this, sweete Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:176864:99"/>of all mercie and comfort, for thy sweete sons and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours sake; to whom with thee and the holy comforter be all honour ascribed, now and euer, Amen.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="prayer">
                     <head>A thankesgiuing to God for the discouerie of treason or faction whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord, maker and possessour of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth, as thou art carefull of thy Saints, so by thy goodnesse the hidden and malitious ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours of Sathan and his seruants against thine annointed and her
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:176864:100"/>people, haue beene and are dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered. In thy iust will, thou mightest haue suffred their rage long before this time to the ruin of all; but it is thy gracious good will, to spare, where thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test punish: good Lord, giue vs soft hearts, that we may tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie sorrowe for sinne, and carrie iust thankes to thee in heart and mouth, for all thy goodnes. For we haue had long and late triall of thy mercie: and by this wee know, that thou fauourest thine annointed, our gracious Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and vs her people com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to her charge, because thou hast not suffered, nor yet sufferest her enimies to haue do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion ouer her. O Lord, make vs thankefull for receiued gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:176864:100"/>that grace may succeede grace, least by ingrateful course thy olde fauours beeing forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, new graces in thy iustice be denied. O Lord, what had been our life, if thou hadst not beene the stay of our life: by thee it is that our life and light yet liueth and shineth, to the spite and malecontment of such as could best bee contented with the quenching of our light and losse of our life. Blessed be thou, O our God, blessed for euer, for thy defence yet continued: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue it still like a prouident God; restraine the rage of men, that it may turne to thy praise by manifesting thy maruellous care ouer thy little, despised, and spited flocke in England.
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:176864:101"/>Be thou our light against darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ourstay against sliding, our might against weakenesse, our castle of defence against al dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rous attempts: be thou our trueth against all treason, our God of peace against rebellion, our wall against forren inuasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, our life against death, and our saluation against intended desolation. Grant long peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and prosperous breath to our gracious Queene Elizabeth; blesse her honourable counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours in all their consultations; blesse her nobility, magistrates, and the commons of this land with faithfull heartes, and with an vnfained touch of true loial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: giue vs new hearts, peace with our selues, and among
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:176864:101"/>our selues in thee, who art the God of peace; that so we may escape their bloudie handes, that in heart, mouth and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise, enuie the peace and pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous state of England. Grant this (deare God) for thine owne sake, wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176864:102"/>
                  <pb n="187" facs="tcp:176864:102"/>
                  <p>A BRIEFE NARRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Dauids case, with <hi>a briefe Application of the</hi> same to the people of England, <hi>whereunto is added what Dauids</hi> disposition was in his condition, <hi>what we should in the like, if we</hi> like and loue the good estate of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</p>
                  <p>Grounded vppon the first part of the 17. v. of the 59. Psalme.</p>
                  <q>Vnto thee, O my strength, will I sing.</q>
                  <p>By <hi>Edw. Hutchins,</hi> one of the <hi>Prebendaries of new Sarum.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="narration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:176864:103"/>
                  <pb n="189" facs="tcp:176864:103"/>
                  <head>A BRIEFE NARRATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON OF DAVIDS CASE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>AVID an elect man, beloued of GOD, a type of Christ his first and best beloued, as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured of happie estate in prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly throne; yet found hee in the world diuers enemies, trouble on euerie side, Saule himselfe did assault him: yea and the particular affaies that he made against Dauid were perillous and great; and that not onely in time of Dauids strength and health, but when he was sicke and kept his bed, he sought the
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:176864:104"/>death of Dauid. From which cruell intent and attempts, not onely did the Prophet make his praier to God for helpe, but by faith he found no lesse then he craued: and therefore with thankes heere hee concludeth this Psalme, magnifying God for his might and mercie in sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him from the furious as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saultes of Saule his mortall foe.</p>
                  <p>For the better sifting of which Scripture, I note two pointes principally.
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1. The Scripture it selfe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2. An application thereof.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> In the first I note two things.
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1. A Promise.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2. A Reason.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> Touching the Promise I note these two pointes.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="191" facs="tcp:176864:104"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1. Something in respect of God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2. Something in respect of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>In respect of God I note,
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1. An Appellation.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2. An Application.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1. He calleth God Strength.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2. His strength.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> For the first point, I note two pointes.
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>1. What name Dauid giues vnto God.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>2. What reason he giues of the same.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> The title is worthy to be noted: that predications are verified of God not only in <hi>concreto</hi> but in <hi>abstracto;</hi> not only (as the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marian speakes) in the adiectiue but in the substantiue: and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, to speake somewhat
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:176864:105"/>darkely, but yet truely and as plainely as I maie: In whome may the substantiue be true but in God? who is in Diuinitie <hi>substantia prima;</hi> and is that on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>nomen substantiuū</hi> that doth <hi>per se subsistere:</hi> all other things are adiectiues without him. To this purpose, as he is called, not onely righteous but righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse it selfe, not only priuatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, because he is voide of sinne, but positiuely, because all righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse is of him, and in him: as he is said to bee sometimes, not only wise but wisedome it selfe, not only by negation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause there is no follie in him, but by assertion, because all wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is in him, and of him: as sometimes not onely <hi>Deus illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minans,</hi>
                     <pb n="193" facs="tcp:176864:105"/>a lightening God, but <hi>lux ipsa,</hi> light it selfe, not onely because there is no darkenes in him, but all light is of him, and in him: as sometimes not only a louing God, or God of loue, but loue it selfe, because he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing, but loueth all things that he hath made: not onely a liuing GOD, but life it selfe, not onely because he is not subiect to age (though the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient of daies) but also because all life is of him, and dependeth vpon him: So here by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet he is called not onely Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, but might, a strong GOD, nay he is called strength it selfe. And iustly, for strength he is: not onely in respect of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, for hee is essentially iust,
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:176864:106"/>wise, light, liuing, louing, strong; and therefore iustice, wisedom, light, life, loue, or as the prophet here cals him strength it selfe: but <hi>Relatiuè,</hi> in respect of the creature vniuersally, and man especially: Almightie in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, of himselfe, and mighty in all. At this time to stand onely vpon the relatiue proofe: God is strength, <hi>quoad esse,</hi> in respect of nature: for who could make all things: from the very worme to the very Angel, from the low Isop to the tall Cedar, from the Leafe to the Oke: and not only so, but made all things without a helper by himselfe, without tooles by his worde, without long time in six daies, and made al things of nothing, but strēgth
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:176864:106"/>it selfe: and therefore what is God but strength? Strength, <hi>quoad conseruari:</hi> for, who is it that could by the power of his word vphold all things, being so many, mighty, and so contrary, but only strength; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what is God but strength it selfe? Oh, why do not the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens fall vpon vs, and the earth faile from vnder vs? who is it that doth or can vphold with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out piller, or else stay in his only hand, heauen, earth, and all the world? It is the marueilous and inestimable worke of God, and the very worke prooues God to be strength it selfe. Thirdlie, strength <hi>quoad dominari:</hi> for who could dispose and gouerne all thinges at will, but onely
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:176864:107"/>trength it selfe? who could on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie by commandement giue the Cloude strength to raine, or the heauens strength to giue show<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? who giues the fire strength to burne? the Sun strength to shine? not any among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles vanities can do it, but only the Lord our God: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what is God, but Strength it selfe? Who can open the doores of Heauen? nay who can deny the heauens Strength to giue dew? Remember the prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Helias: or the fire it selfe strength to burne? Remember Moyses, and the Bushe: or the Sun it selfe strength to stop or run? Remember Iosua and his prayer: or restraine the Lyons strength to feed? Remember
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:176864:107"/>Daniel in his den: who coulde by a very Rauen releeue a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet in the time of neede, but only God? And therefore what is God but Strength it selfe? VVho coulde smite the Rocke, though neuer so hard, and make it ouerflowe with Streames? who could giue the Wheate of Heauen, and feede man in his hunger with Manna, the bread of Angels? Who could diuide the Sea, &amp; make it to stand like a heape, that his people might haue way to passe? Who could raine flesh as dust, and feathered fowle as the sand of the sea, but onely strength; and therefore what is God but strength? To be short, the winde doth blow, the sea doth ebbe and flow: the
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:176864:108"/>moone decreaseth, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couers strength of light and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creases: All thinges haue their vertue, and strength, but yet in god the strength of al. Strength? For in God the weakest things are strong; a Frogge to feare a Pharao: a hand to feare a Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thazar; a worme too mighty for a Herode: the shaking leafe may terrify a sinner: in him Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias is too weak for Dauids sling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone, the Philistine for Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons Iawbone: the little flocke of Iesu Christ sufficeth against <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Foxe, and his drop to swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low vp the floude of Antichrist.</p>
                  <p>And therefore, what is God but strength it selfe? Strength? without whome the strongest thinges are weake: the Whale
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:176864:108"/>restores and cannot keepe a Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas: the Lyons strength is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to a Dauid: the Caterpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, Flie and Grashopper are of sufficient power to amaze the power of Aegypt. Holofernes fought for the proud god of the world, but God fought against him, and chopt off his head to the shame of his dust god, by the hand of Iudith, a woman, a widowe. All strength and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is of him, and therefore if he withdraw his power, no power is left to any thing: the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens prooue to be as brasse, the earth cannot be fruitfull: or if it bee, yet is he of that strength, that hee is able to destroye the vine with haile, and the wilde figtree with hailestones:
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:176864:109"/>he is able to giue our cattell to the haile, and our flockes vnto the thunderbolts: he can forsake vs, as he did Shilo, and make the Philistine sufficient against vs: he can deliuer his power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to captiuitie, and his beauty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the enemies hand: and when he hath done, he can awake as one out of sleepe, and as a strong man, that after his wine crieth out, to smite his enemies on the hinder parts, and put them to a perpetuall shame. Oh, what shall I say? The Diuell himselfe is called not onely wicked, but spirituall wickednesse, not only strong; but power, principality it selfe, the Prince and God of the world; and yet what is his strength? The very pigge is safe
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:176864:109"/>from such a Prince, from all his power and threat, vnlesse the Lorde doe giue him strength: And therefore what is God but strength it selfe? Nay, what is man but dust; and what is dust but weake to withstand a strong winde, yea or a puffe? and what is the hayre of mans head, but weaker then man? And yet the Diuell is so weake, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not vexe man no nor pluck one hayre from his head; hee dare not lay any hands vpon a Iob, vnlesse he borrow strength of God: And therfore what is God but strength it selfe? Strength? For, who could ouermatch the Kite by a Henne; the Hawke by a Sparrow? the hungrie Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by a Lambe? principality by
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:176864:110"/>weaknesse? The God of the world by a Crosse? The God of death, by the death of life? Who could ouermatch the diuell by his sonnes infirmitie? to speake the mighty worke of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: who could feede men by hunger? refresh them by thirst? releeue the wanter by want? Who could strengthen by wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rines? cloathe man by naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? crowne man by a Crosse? iuslifie, and saue man from the Lord of death by the death of life, of Christ his Sonne, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie God? And of all works, this strong worke prooueth the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel of himselfe to be weake, and God to be strength. Howbeit, this appeareth to bee true, not onely <hi>quoad caput,</hi> but <hi>quoad
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:176864:110"/>corpus.</hi> For if God be strength against the diuel, power it selfe; what is he (to the proofe of the point) but strength against the powers of the world, who are subordinate vnto him? Indeed the powers of the world may set themselues, as they doe against his seruants: but what then? all wisedome is folly, all strength is infirmitie, vnlesse God giue strength, all flesh is as light as vanity, and what can vanitie doe? But to followe the point: Dauid cals God Strength, and his strength. Here is the 2 point, where I note 3. pointes, <hi>1. a Commendation, 2. a Collection, 3. a Confirmation. 1, A commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> of Dauid, who doth not call God indefinitely strength
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:176864:111"/>vvhich all Creatures in their manner, are bound to confesse; but he cals him Strength, and his strength: he makes applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the name, wherein I find the faith of Dauid: for the nature of a true and liuely faith doth not rest in generall veritie, but doth apply: for otherwise where is the difference between mens Faith, and diuels faith? which doeth not apply, but resteth vppon generall veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Collection therefore in the 2. is,</hi> that all the Elect, and therefore wee, if wee count our selues Elect, must do as Dauid here doth: wee must not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our selues to beleeue gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, but wee must apply and
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:176864:111"/>call GOD Strength, and our Strength. Thus Thomas could beleeue, and beleeuing apply, my Lord, and my God: Thus Paul could beleeue, and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing apply, Christ loued mee, and gaue himselfe forme: Thus Iob coulde beleeue, and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing apply, I am sure that my Redeemer liueth: Thus Dauid here doth beleeue, and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing could apply: <hi>Vnto thee O my strength will I sing:</hi> And thus with Dauid wee must be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and beleeuing apply, or else wee beleeue vnprofitablie. Ferus writing vpon the 19. of Iob, saith thus: Reade (saith he) what Iob speakes: he saith not I am sure y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a Redeemer liueth, but I am sure that my Redeemer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth:
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:176864:112"/>this is emphaticall (sayth he: <hi>Quid enim ad me quod Christus redemptor sit nisi meus quoque sit redemptor, nisi me quoque redemptionis suae fece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit participem? nouit quippè Satanas Christum redemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orem esse; sed suum redemptorem eum appellare non potest. Ad hanc igitur discamus rectè for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare fidem nostram: non suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, si credamus, nisi &amp; cum fiducia quadam credamus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And so say I; if wee will bee saued as Dauid was, wee must beleeue as Dauid did, God to be God, and our God: Strength and our strength. And why not? for what was God, but Dauids strength; yea, and the strength of all Dauids, of all the
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:176864:112"/>Elect? For alas, what had Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid beene to Saule his foe? or what are Gods annointed to the wicked? in number so manie, in power so mighty, in affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on so malicious, and open prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise so merciles, were not God their strength, which is the strength of al. But yet, though in briefe, to open the point: what were the best Paul, to the buffets of his owne flesh? what were the best Iob to beare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him and out, his sory coale of sores? what were the stou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Esay to feele and suffer the saw within his bowels? what were the best Latimer, or anie of Christes little ones to fight, not onely with fire and fagot, with the diuels Bonners, and
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:176864:113"/>bodily diuels: but also with the diuell himselfe, the God and Prince of death and darknesse, were not God their light to comfort, their strength to vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stay and defend them? To this purpose God hath often giuen the godly feeling and sense of their infirmity: Paul himselfe coulde not beare a buffet, and yet the grace of God made him sufficient: Iob, the Mirrour of patience, sometimes grewe to impatience; and yet the Lord so strengthened him by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of patience, that hee could protest, that hee would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce him, although hee would kill him. The very god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liest haue cried oft in trouble, and thought God too long in
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:176864:113"/>deferring his helpe: <hi>Domine quousque?</hi> and yet the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all hope, to the better triall of his Saints infirmity, and of his owne strength, hath come at length to helpe and to rescue them.</p>
                  <p>Shall I say all? God is their strength, and so strong in them and for them, as passeth al con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and vnderstanding. For, where the condition of Gods seruants seemeth hard and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable, yet God is strength it selfe, and turneth their very misery to the good and felicitie of them that are his. The diuell hath a sword for Abell; a sharp and biting bedde of ashes for a Iob; nothing but a sory coate of sores for a Lazarus, no want of
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:176864:114"/>want for his belly: a blocke hee hath for Baptists head, Stephen founde and felt his stones, and Peter found a girdle of chaines. <hi>Act. 12.</hi> Nothing hath the di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uel but a presse for our Sauiours Grape. a fornace for his Gold, a slaughter-house for his lambes, dogges to deuoure his dearling. Dauid was indangered in time of health, and in his bed: Oh, when shall Dauid die, or the Name of Dauid perish? The Diuel hath nothing but marks and great trouble, for all that ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Seale of the liuing God in their foreheades; and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding God is strength it selfe, and so strong, that hee makes all safe, and their estate in him to bee secure, and sure
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:176864:114"/>against the gates of hell, that beate against him. Yea so sure, that he bringeth them, by their sorrowes to ioie, by their paines from paine to eternall pleasure, by a cuppe of vineger to pledge Christ in a cuppe of new wine in heauen; by losse to gaine, by darkenesse to light, by wounds to health, by their crossing from all crosse to the crowne of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall glory. And howsoeuer Sathan assault them and seeme to insult and exult ouer, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them; yet indeed he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not oppresse, though he presse them: he maye nibble at their heeles, but his owne heade is broken, and theirs can he not breake: nay, indeed against his will, the Diuel doth them good,
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:176864:115"/>when he doth presse them. For, the gold of God is purest in the furnace; his wheat cleerest when it is winowed: Iohn Baptist may loose his head vppon earth, and findes the sooner a better head in heauen: God is strength, and in spite of the Diuell hee workes the very infirmities, pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, and death of his Saints to their good; who is otherwise strong, if he will, when he will, and as he will, to deliuer them frō bodily trouble: as he could and did to the proofe of his strength deliuer Noe from the waters, Lot from the Sodomits Susanna by Daniell, Daniell from the Lyons, Peter from the prison, Paule from Nero, and Dauid from Saule.</p>
                  <pb n="213" facs="tcp:176864:115"/>
                  <p>And, if he please not to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his temporally, yet is hee a strong God to deliuer them spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, and eternally. He is to his seruaunts this way without faile, in discomfort a consolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his spirit is a comforter, his spirit is their guide and crier. Abba Father, is proclaimed in their hearts, they are sure by life and death to haue aduauntage by Christ: their very death they know to be precious: in a word, by many troubles he makes an end of their trouble; he makes their death a sweete sleepe to their bodies; and a way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their soules come the sooner to his presence. And therefore what is God but strength? He was the strength of Dauid, and
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:176864:116"/>is the onely strength of all that will be saued. But of this more hereafter. Thus we see the name of strength by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Prophet giuen to God: howbeit in this place the Prophet doth call him his strength in speciall respect of his power, whereby he saued him and secured him from Saule, that dogge that gaped to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure him: as appeares by the Prophetes reason, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines a restraint.</p>
                  <p>Now therefore, what doth the Prophet promise to God his strength? I will sing to thee. First he promiseth to sing: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is lawfull to sing, yea and godly: but yet vpon like occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion as Dauid had. For Dauid promiseth nothing heere, but
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:176864:116"/>what good was, and vppon a good ground: and (as we read in the New Testament) Christ with his disciples song a psalme. Yea, and it is lawfull and godly to sing not onely in priuate pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but in publike assemblies: yea, and to sing to the Organ: as the verie word (Psalme) doth plainely prooue against the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise men of our time, though <hi>cantus operosus,</hi> if it runne notes without heart, be vtterly vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. But, to go on: Dauid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseth a song and to sing vnto God: vnto him, as if hee had said: Though Saule haue assaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and sought to slaie me; and my heart in that respect might be heauie and my soule disquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within me: yet, good Lord,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:176864:117"/>I knowe that all flesh is grasse, and man but dust, and dust is nothing vnto thee, who art my strength, and hast saued mee by thy strength: therefore will I sing and be ioiful in thee.</p>
                  <p>A point of discretion and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in Dauid, and Gods Saintes after trouble and deliuerance, to giue iust thanks. So when A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham returned frō his slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Melchisedec the high priest mette Abraham, and saide: Blessed be the high GOD, by whose aide thine enimies are in thy hand. <hi>Gen. 14.</hi> So vppon the conquest of Sisera, Debora, and Barach, sung and saide: Whosoeuer they are that haue willingly offred themselues to danger, Blesse yee the Lorde.
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:176864:117"/>
                     <hi>Iudic. 5.</hi> Second part applieth. And therefore to make vse of this Scripture: was euer Dauid more spited by Saule then our Dauid hath beene and is? Did the floud seeke to rush vppon him, and not vpon her? Hath not priuie perill beene within our walles? Is not Saule open in heart, and in open warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vs? Hath not the spiritual Saul of Rome, yea &amp; his greatest fauorite of Spaine, yea and that vnder the pretence of successiue right in religion to Peter and Paul, not only spoken the word, but drawne the sword vpon vs? What shal I say? was euer spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row so farre past hope in Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers eye? was euer lambe more in danger of the Foxe in Foxes
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:176864:118"/>eie, then our gracious princesse, her people, and countrey hath beene, and is in the will and eye of her foes? Indeed the Diuell of olde threatened, but nowe knowing his time to bee short, he makes the time sharpe, and seekes not by perswasion, but by open force desolation to our Sion, vtter ruin to our wals, cruel death to come to the verye babes of our Bethleem: to bring vs for plenty, scarcenesse; for peace, war; for mirth, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninesse; for life, death and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of them: all his vvhole study is to make our sweete wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters bitter; our acceptable daies, daies of weeping and wailing. Oh, what is practised to the vtmost power and spite
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:176864:118"/>of Pope and Spaniard and their fauourites without and within our walles, but feare of wo, yea and fulnes of woe to the good estate of England? priuily, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillously, diuersly, of old, lately, almost how presently hath the matter beene attempted. But to proceed, I appeale to you al; how is it that Saule hath assaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and yet hath not preuailed? how is it that our Dauid was in danger, and yet hath escaped? how hath the snare beene bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? the fowler caught, and the sparrow beene saued? how hath Iudas kissed the gallowes, that came by a kisse to betray vs into the hands of our enimies? I need not to assure you that the Saule of Rome and Spaine
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:176864:119"/>haue mumbled vp their masses apace, hoped and groned for the contrary: there hath beene no sparing of Indian treasure vpon treason at home, and force from abroade, to worke their spitefull and bloudy hope. And therefore where Saule hath not seene his lamentable wishe, darkenesse, where light; warre, where peace; the sword, where quietnes as yet of Gods mercy and goodnesse is among vs; surely I cannot giue any cause hereof, but Dauids cause: God is Strength, and hath beene our strength; for many a day before this day the Foxe had worried our Lambe; our Vine blossomes had beene destroyed, the loue of God had beene awaked; yea,
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:176864:119"/>and banished: that woman of the Reuerlation had beene as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saulted, yea, and driuen to the Desarte: wee had all wished Doues wings to flee far enough for some rest. Shall I say all? Our daies had beene ful of woe, our state had beene as Daniels state among the Lyons: nay, no lesse then Abels; the sword had beene in our bowelles, had not the Almighty beene our mighty GOD, our strength to cut off Caine, that spited his Abel, and thirsted after his innocent blood among vs. And surely as all Nations may call GOD their strength (for all power is of him;) but most truely, and to their comfort, such as fauour the truth of God, and do harbour
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:176864:120"/>his fauourites; (for they are as mount Sion, God himselfe is their wal, they cannot be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued:) so among and aboue all other christian countries vnder the coape of heauen, we maie for ours truely and most thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully call God our strength.</p>
                  <p>For, where in other countries there is not only question about the true candlesticke of Christ, whether it be golden or not; but also, whether it shall stand, where it is most certainelye knowne to bee golden: and, to that purpose, the Saule of Rome hath got in his foote, and by the force of forraine power or false course at home hopes to be full head; and hath attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted no lesse then to border a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:176864:120"/>vs: and to the same pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose hath had his Iesuites and Priests to play the Iudasses at home and externe power pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to helpe the practise; and yet hath been kept off oft and very strangely from vs; surely we thanke none but God: God? for hee is strength, hath beene, and is our onely strength: no mans might or pollicie, but his owne right hand hath done it. Our God is in heauen, and doth whatsoeuer hee will, and hath done of good will vnto vs, more then for any people now liuing.</p>
                  <p>To passe then on, from point to point: seeing that God hath beene the defence of this our land, and for the comfort there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hath made his strength appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:176864:121"/>and knowne to all the world: seeing, that to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose beyond the reach of mans conceit and Diuels hope, hee hath these many yeeres kept, and still keeps the state of sweet Elizabeth, whose daies God long and long maintain against the hope of vnhappy Saule or rebellious spirites, that gape for an ende of our peace for our woes without ende. Oh what shall I do, but with the Prophet promise, and performe heartie thankes vnto God? let vs sing a new song and reioice in God our strength, for the happy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of England. Let our state therefore (deere beloued) be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer before our eies, let our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance bee alwaies fresh in
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:176864:121"/>our memories, let vs neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get Gods eies, and might in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of vs; and let vs all and alwaies praise him for the good estate of England.</p>
                  <p>Let vs remember other nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons how they lie in darkenesse, in superstition and blindnesse: howe the people are polluted, and by authority permitted, yea and forced to follow after Baa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim how they are like the swift Dromedarie that runneth by his waies, running alwaies to and fro to worship their Idols both in valley, and hill. <hi>Ier. 2.</hi> how they playe the spirituall har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots their kings, princes, priests, Prophets, and people say to a tree thou art our Father, and to a stone thou hast begotten vs:
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:176864:122"/>how they haue their Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their number of their Cities, and withall howe God hath planted and kept vs; how he hath placed his golden can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlesticke, and his starre giueth light in this our land, in spite of the Serpent of Rome, and Lyon of Spaine: and let vs all, and alwaies sing due praises vnto him for the good estate of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
                  <p>Let vs remember in other Countries, howe Saule is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, and hath drawne his Sword; and not only bids bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, but also for the sinnes of the people, cuts off the heads, and visible staies of the Church: Let vs remember howe the glory of Iacob was turned away, howe
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:176864:122"/>the emptiers emptied them out, and marred their Vine branches: <hi>Mich. 2.</hi> And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al let vs not but remember how the waters of Queene Maries daies were turned to comfort in sweete Elizabethes time, and be not as yet turned to bloud: our bones cleaue not to our skinne: the voice of our groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is not so great as yet: wee haue not beene as yet as Owles of the Desart, or bottels in the smoke, though Dauid himselfe were so; we be in our houses, and not on the tops watching and left as sparrowes alone.</p>
                  <p>To be short, in merite you knowe ashes might bee our bread, but wee haue not eaten them; God hath preserued, and
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:176864:123"/>yet doth, the peace of our Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem against the conspiracies and cruell intents of all the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: and therefore let vs al, and alwaies praise him for the good estate of England.</p>
                  <p>Let vs remember our long plenty and peace, our manifold blessings by land and Sea these many yeares; how oft, and how woonderfully God hath beene for vs: how dangerously Saule hath assaulted, and yet howe strongly and strangely GOD hath saued vs: that, howsoeuer Pope or Spaniard threaten and breathe, yet their breathing is hindered by sweete Elizabeths breath; (vnder him the breath of vs all:) and let vs all, and alwayes sing vnto him, and
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:176864:123"/>praise him for this good estate of England.</p>
                  <p>Lastly, let vs remember that God hath knocked these many yeares, and yet doth, at the hart of euery one for true repentance and amendment of life: howe long, and how loath he is to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish vs in rigor. Let vs neuer forget his gentle knockes, and cals by his manifolde mercies, yea, and of late yeares by shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per threat of warres, by death. Oh, let vs remember howe for our sinnes he hath sent a dearth, a famine in the lande: yet in mercy and so, that hee hath not vtterly broken the staffe of bread, though some wanted, yet Israel hath his Ioseph in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a place: and it is the will of
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:176864:124"/>our gratious Princesse, that Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael shall haue his Ioseph in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place: and if in euery place her Maiesties good will to her Subiects be not performed, let vs pray to GOD to amende what is amisse, that God may continue our thankes to him for the good estate of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
                  <p>So shall wee doe what his mercy deserueth; so shall wee do what the glory of his strength of right forceth from vs; so shal we do that whereunto duetie bindeth vs, and this example of good Dauid leades vs, if wee take vp our song and praise God our strength for the good estate of England. Yea, and seeing that Dauid did it, a man elect
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:176864:124"/>to be a Prophet and a King, let vs all do it: for God hath beene and is our generall strength of our prophets, people, yea and of our Dauid: the peril hath not bin particular, but generall, and so hath been the escape: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the Prophets, people, yea and rulers, yea and the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Dauid of this our Land, are bounde to sing continuall thankes to GOD our onely strength, for the preuenting of our woes, for the confounding of our foes, for his diuers and vndeserued defence of the pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous state of England.</p>
                  <p>But (alas) here what shall I say? there was neuer any na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnder the cope of Heauen more blessed then this our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:176864:125"/>hath beene and is; neuer had a lande a Princesse more gracious: neuer was any church any where more wonderfully preserued and defended: (for neuer had any countrey more close &amp; malicious foes at home, more stout and desperate ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies abroad:) and yet neuer was Gods mercie more mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest in the defence of any, then of this our land: (Oh, besides o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther blessings singular and sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie, which I doe not repeate:) and, yet where is he or shee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most that singes to GOD our strength, thankes him for his mercie, and doth praise it for the good estate of England?</p>
                  <p>What shall I say? as yet wee are not in Daniels denne; the
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:176864:125"/>Viper as yet hath not lighte vppon our hands: Abednago was in the Ouen, but so were neuer we: Peter walked on the waters, and so haue we; but Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter began to sinke, and so did neuer we: Our Sauiours hande that saued Peter from sinking, hath saued England, that as yet we haue not begun to sinke: for this mercie the sacrifice of praise is due, but where is it offered? the cup of saluation should be taken in hand, but who takes it? the sacrifice should be bound with coards to the hornes of the Altar; but who bindes it? Nay, alas, were not for his owne sake, who hath been our strength, so many be the Peters of England, that are so ful of doubling in the
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:176864:126"/>point of religion, that wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serue no better then sinking.</p>
                  <p>For, runne ouer all places and persons, and what shal you find? In all Sodome there were not ten righteous to be found: in Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da one righteous man could not be found: <hi>Ier. 5.</hi> Micheas loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for a cluster, <hi>Ca. 6.</hi> of grapes, but he found not one: but alas, if we run to and fro by the streets of England, and looke into most of the open places thereof, we shall hardly finde one grape: how shall we finde a cluster? I will not say, that the best is a brier, and most righteous shar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per then a thorne: but this I say, many are on earth, but few that haue their mindes set vpon God our strength in heauen. For,
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:176864:126"/>what may wee finde in euerie place but no thankes? nay, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most no thinking of GOD; so godlesse wee are, and thankles and thinkelesse of him, though our onely strength, that hath vpholden and still doeth, the prosperous state of England.</p>
                  <p>For, alas, for one sonne, how many bee our prodigals? for one Peter that sinnes and doth weepe, how many be our Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that heare the cocke crowe and yet do sinne, and do sleepe? for one Zacheus that makes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, oh how many be our Publicanes, that delight in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion? for one Iob that pities the poore, how many be they that for their own priuate gaine studie howe to make others as
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:176864:127"/>poore as euer was Iob? Nay are we not growne to be vnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall? What say wee to long baire, and to the vncut head of cutters? are we not growne to this miserable case, that we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse pride, which is of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell? wee are proude in our lookes, proude in our gates, proud in our speeches, proud in our diet, proud in our building: Oh, we haue forgotten dust our mother! Oh, what shal I say? In stead of truth, lying is common; in stead of religious feare, swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is common; in stead of loue, malice, yea muther is common; in stead of chastnes, how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is wantonnes, in stead of free-giuing and lending, howe common is couetousnesse and
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:176864:127"/>vsury? Alas, what is now more common then to commit sinne, yea to professe it, and without all shame to defend it? GOD was neuer more mercifull and mighty towardes vs, and yet were we neuer so thanklesse: oh where is he or she almost, that with pure and penitent heart, sings due praise vnto him for the good estate of England? Nay (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las) there is such generall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption among vs: such spite in hart, such vainenesse and bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in words, such falsenes and cruelty in deeds, such watching to do euil, &amp; slacknes to do good in all: such scantnesse of faith, coldnes of loue in euery place: after so much preaching of the Gospell, yet so little care of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending:
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:176864:128"/>To be short, there is after so many marueilous and manifest trials of Gods mercie and strength towards vs in sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs, yet so little care to thank him; yea, or almost to thinke vpon him; that I feare, least we by our sins shall prouoke God to anger, indeede to make an end of the good estate of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. For, no doubt, our sinnes that are many, are mighty; and as they are mighty, so they mightily crie to God for our woe: and howe can they but crie? seeing that wee sinne, and yet do know that the figles fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree that was green with leaues, was cursed, and did wither: how can they but crie? seeing that we sinne, and yet do know
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:176864:128"/>that there is an ax to hew down the barren tree, and vnquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable fire to burne the chaffe: how can they but crie? seeing that we sinne, and yet do know, that before the wicked shall want a rod, the creature it selfe will rise vp in open armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him: the wicked to drowne, though it bee a whole world; the fire to burne though it bee all Sodome: the earth to swallowe vp a Core; the very worme to gnawe the bowels, though it be of Antiochus: the heauen it selfe to frowne, and the earth it selfe to lowre vpon our corne, grasse, cattel, or other creature to deceiue vs. Oh how can our sinnes but crie, seeing that we sinne, and yet do know,
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:176864:129"/>that it wee seeke not first the Kingdome of God, God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not long minister his blessinges vnto vs. For to him that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth what it is to doe well, how to doe it, and doeth it not, to him it is a sinne, a greater sin, indeed a mighty and crying sin: and yet (alas) thus it is; men take small care to repent, which is the next way to preuent woe. For, howe slacke are men to come to Church daily, to heare the word reuerently, to reforme their liues accordingly, to think vpon their dutie, to thanke God for his strengthe and mercie, which yet is the next and onely way to make secure, and for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer sure the prosperous state of England.</p>
                  <pb n="241" facs="tcp:176864:129"/>
                  <p>Alas dearely beloued, this should not be so: our God who hath beene our strength, hath deserued better thanks then so: and if we will not learne to giue him better thankes, hee cannot choose but take his mercy from vs, and bestow it vppon some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation, that shall giue him better then so. For what? shal the worde of God bee cast be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind our backes? shall men sweare among vs, ei her by no gods, or vainely, or falsely, and commonly by the true and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God? Shall words bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, which are cloathed with death? shall adulterous men &amp; whormong rs be in the land to whom al bread is sweet? shall bloud touch bloud? shall
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:176864:130"/>men breake out by swearing and lying and killing, and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring? shall the Diuels seruice be so common from them that professe the true seruice of Christ? and shall not the Lord visite vs for these thinges? shall not his soule be auenged vppon such a Nation as this? Surely without hearty and speedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, the Lorde cannot spare vs for this; but hee will make the Land mourne, and euerie one that dwelleth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, will hee cutte off, with the beastes of the Fielde, and the fowles of the Heauen, and also the fishes of the sea shal he take away. For if we haue sinned, and do sinne against him, as his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits were increased and are
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:176864:130"/>vpon vs; so what will followe but a change of our glorie into shame? for he that worketh e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill shall be wrapped in euill; vexation lurketh for him as a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Ecclesiast. 27.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And therefore, sith it would do you no good to see the lamp of God put out, that nowe shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth among vs: the glorie of the Lord to lie in the dust: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but death to your owne bowelles, and death to your children: nothing but sworde and shedding bloud in our eies: nothing but howling and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in your streetes: if rather you wish the good estate of the land; then from this time forwards see that ye renounce your sins haue vnderstanding, that this lande
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:176864:131"/>may be still, and let your feet be ofte in the house of your God; giue eare to his word, that you may walke in his law and in the waies of his commandements: amend your liues and be thank full vnto him. Oh remember the manifold blessings he hath vouchsafed you: what peace? what plenty these many yeeres? what a Church, what a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous princesse, what a nurse, what a mother, how long and how oft, of old and how lately he hath beene her staffe, and in her, our strength and stay, our defence and merciful God? and see that you all sing iust praise vnto him, for this good estate of England.</p>
                  <p>And then, so dooing, I can
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:176864:131"/>and doe assure you, that howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer Saul be abroad and hopes to be at vs and to worke his will on vs; his will? which is to wash vs all, man, woman and childe, in our owne hearts bloud; yet shall he neuer obtaine his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose: Christ himselfe will bee your rocke, neither shall winde nor water ouerthrow you. By men of vnderstanding the Citie is inhabited, <hi>Eccle. 16.</hi> The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent haue deliuered Ilands, and shall deliuer England: they shall be as mount Sion, that shal neuer be remoued; they shall be vnto God, as the apple of his owne eie, that shall be secure; the Lord himselfe will fight for them; and hee will bee your strength by lande and sea, to
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:176864:132"/>maintaine still the prosperous state of England.</p>
                  <p>But perhaps some will saie, that their forces are strong, their preparations long, their treasure is great, and as it in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth, so increase they in malice: men are false, and malecontents now adaies: <hi>Et ad quid non mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talia pectora cogit auri sacra fames?</hi> They will doe almost any thing vppon Iudas point, vppon what you will giue mee; and so they reason, but yet without reason, in doubt of anie continuance of the good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of England.</p>
                  <p>For I answere easily; be our aduersaries neuer so strong, be they neuer so crafty, let the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, Iesuites and Seminaries,
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:176864:132"/>with their Catholike Caine of Spaine, and Caiphas of Rome do what they can; yet do you as good Dauid did: call vppon God, and heartily thanke him for his mercy and might in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of you for the time past: and then will God still maintain our cause, or rather his owne: Pope or Spaniard may do their worst: and yet God is strength, hee is able to breake the iron. <hi>Ier. 15.</hi> He can and will be our strength, to crush them like the leafe, and turne them like pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vesselles into dust. And though perhaps they think they dwell in the clefts of the rockes, and take their habitation to be high, and say in their harts, who shall bring vs downe to the
<pb n="248" facs="tcp:176864:133"/>ground? yet what then? vpon our repentance and thankefull seruice, assure your selues that the pride of their heartes shall deceiue them. He which spared not the old Gentils, which were rebellious, and trusted in their owne strength; neither spared wheras Lot dwelt, those whom he abhorred for their pride; the same God will bee mighty to forgiue vs our sinnes, and giue vs peace, and mighty to powre out displeasure against your eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: he will smite the head o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer great countries, that smites at all Christian heads, that hee might be a Monarch; and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to haue your desire vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, that you may still enioy the happy estate of England.</p>
                  <pb n="249" facs="tcp:176864:133"/>
                  <p>Otherwise I will bee plaine with you; if the slacknes of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and of amendment of life be continued amongst vs, which now is so generall; if you will not learne, in stead of excesse to be abstinent; in stead of lust, to be continent; in stead of hatred, to loue; in stead of reuenge, to forgiue; in stead o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vsury, to lend freely and giue; in stead of impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etie and sinne, to learne the practise of pietie and religious life, or godlie conuersation; to be short; if Gods mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, and strength for vs by land and Sea, be still forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, which of olde and of late time hath bin, and yet is so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest manifold and marueilous, to the view of the whole world;
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:176864:134"/>if we do not open our mouthes, and that of fashion or shewe onely, (which is the common and bad fashion of most;) but also with hearty and true deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to sing to him due praise for it: Surely it cannot bee, but God will at length put songes of lamentation into your hearts and mouthes; his iustice can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not spare to shorten the prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous state of England.</p>
                  <p>And to reward vs with the feares that without speedy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance are to bee feared; in stead of light, with darknes; in stead of Manna, with the flesh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pottes of Aegypt; in stead of prosperity, with want; in stead of peace, with warre; in stead of Christ the true vine, with the
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:176864:134"/>thistle of Rome to pricke vs in our side, if not to runne thorow vs.</p>
                  <p>And therefore men, Fathers, and Brethren, beloued in the Lord; thinke vpon your selues, and vppon your Children; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the daies wherein you haue liued and liue; remember Saule what and how he threats; remember what Caines he hath had abroad and among vs, and perhaps yet hath, who waite for Abels throate to cut it: how ready they are, and howe they grieue and groane to sucke the bloode of Abell like rauenous Dogges: remember how God hath bin and yet is our strength and buckler: and thorow and in him, how man and wife, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="252" facs="tcp:176864:135"/>and child, old and yoong, the basest and best haue posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, do and onely can possesse the peace and ioie of the Land, and see that hereafter you serue the Lord, continue this your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sorting to seruice and sermons: pray vnto God for his mercy and might for the time present and to come, and sing prayse vnto him for his manifold mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and manifested might for the time past: so shall you bee sure in spite of spiteful Pope and Spaniard, Papist and Atheist whatsoeuer, to enioy still the happy estate of England.</p>
                  <p>But here perhappes as some will say vnto me; what needes all this, we haue continued in our sinnes these and these many
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:176864:135"/>yeares, and men are so far from singing thankes vnto God for the peace of England, that most do neuer or seldome thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God, but vppon the world, and vppon their owne gaine: and yet we haue enioied, and still doe enioy the prosperous state of England.</p>
                  <p>I answere indeede, that as God hath beene mercifull from time to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me in beeing our strēgth, so the most haue scarce thought vpon his goodnes and strength in sauing of vs: howe few are they that haue thought or thinke vpon our memorable and late deliuery from the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish force by Seas, yea and of our later successe against the Paul and Philip of Spaine: and
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:176864:136"/>yet notwithstanding all this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankefulnes, we enioy still the good estate of England: and hereupon the wicked presume to be graceles, because God is good and gracious, and doeth not by and by punish. But I answere first, that as I reade of people among he Iewes: <hi>Ier.</hi> 7. They would steale, murder, and commit adultery, sweare falsely, and burne incense to Baal, and walke after vnknown gods: and yet they would come and stand before God in his house, whereuppon his name was called, and say; we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, though we haue doone all these abhominations: So (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las) it is amongst many in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; when they heare without
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:176864:136"/>repentaunce the worde of the curse, they blesse themselues in their hearts, saying: VVee shall haue peace, although wee walke according to the stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornnesse of our owne heartes: thus adding drunkennes to thirst, a pitifull thing: shall the Lord be mercifull to such men? shall not his wrath and ielousie at length breake out against such?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, though it bee so, that many and multitudes of thanklesse persons bee among vs; yet I hope wee haue had and haue yet some Dauids a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs, some thankfull harts, that doe not forgette to prayse GOD for his mercy, and pray still for his strength: and for
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:176864:137"/>their sakes I doubt not but God hath continued, and yet doeth continue, the happy estate of England.</p>
                  <p>And as for the wicked, I pray GOD giue them better heartes, thankefull heartes like to Dauids heart, or at least to decrease the number of them: otherwise I appeale to you all: what do the practises of diuers at home, and the professed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of foes abroad, but in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner threaten present punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for our slackenes in ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of God, and singing praise vnto him? Oh, what do they say in effect to euery hart, but feare? VVee are the messengers of Gods iustice to England, vnles England repent and learne to
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:176864:137"/>thanke God for his goodnes in preseruing of it.</p>
                  <p>Oh, therefore liue no waye carelesse of duty and thanklesse to God: but from this time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, let the feare of God be in your heartes and with the Prophet carrie his praise in your lippes: so ought you to doe, yea and so will you doe if the glorie of our daies, if the grace of this our accepted time be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of you, and deare in your eies; if indeede you tender the prosperous estate of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</p>
                  <p>God therefore of his mercie grant vs that we may all thinke vpon dutie, to praise him for all his blessings powred vpon vs, and withall to praie vnto him,
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:176864:138"/>as he hath beene, so still to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue our strength.</p>
                  <p>O Lorde, giue long breath to thy seruant, our gracious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse Elizabeth. Strengthen her people by land and sea; giue them grace to serue thee, that they may be strong in thee, The wicked haue said it in their hearts, and sworne it with their mouthes, and sealed their oath by their false named sacrifice, and drie god of bread, that there is no strength to saue Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land from them. But (O God) thou art strength, thou wast Dauids strength, our strength thou hast beene, our trust is in thee: let vs neuer be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: be still our defence, and our mercifull God: And giue
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:176864:138"/>vs grace to be thankfull to thee, to sing due praise to thy name, that so by thee our strength, we may still enioy the blessed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state of England.</p>
                  <p>And as for all them that bee enemies, either priuate, or open, thou art strength it selfe, O Lorde, thou canst, and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seech thee (if thy will be so) to conuert them; if not, O God our strength, in thy strength confound them, and to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels spite and ioy of thy seruants continue by sweete Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths life the prosperous state of England, Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:176864:139"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176864:139"/>
            <head>¶ A Catalog <hi>contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the seueral titles of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> praier, and treatise compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed in this booke, easie to be found by the true number of the Page.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Confession of sinne, pag. 1</item>
               <item>2 A praier for remission of sinne. 3</item>
               <item>3 A praier for mortification. 5</item>
               <item>4 A praier for amendment of life. 7</item>
               <item>5 A complaint, with a praier against sinne. 11</item>
               <item>6 A comfortable meditation in
<pb facs="tcp:176864:140"/>time of temptation. 13</item>
               <item>7 A praier for peace. 16</item>
               <item>8 A praier for peace of consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. 20</item>
               <item>9 A comfortable praier in time of aduersitie. 23</item>
               <item>10 A praier against despera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 26</item>
               <item>11 A praier for Chastitie. 35</item>
               <item>12 A praier for the good bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vp of Children. 49</item>
               <item>13 A praier for watchfulnesse against Sathan. 51</item>
               <item>14 A necessarie praier for our time and for all christians. page. 54</item>
               <item>15 Another. 59</item>
               <item>16 A praier after the hearing of the word preached. 67</item>
               <item>17 A thanksgiuing to God for his benefits. 69</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:176864:140"/>
               <item>18 A praier for the feare of God. 72</item>
               <item>19 A praier for courage against the feare of the wicked. 74</item>
               <item>20 A praier for patience. 77</item>
               <item>21 A praier against pride. 79</item>
               <item>22 A praier against sinfull an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. 82</item>
               <item>23 A praier for godly anger. page. 85</item>
               <item>24 A praier against gluttonie. page. 87</item>
               <item>25 A praier against couetous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse. 91</item>
               <item>26 A praier against bribes. 93</item>
               <item>27 A praier against discord and malice. 96</item>
               <item>28 A praier for true loue. 100</item>
               <item>29 A praier for hospitality. 102</item>
               <item>30 A praier for grace to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke sinne in the wicked.
<pb facs="tcp:176864:141"/>page. 108</item>
               <item>31 A praier for the grace of compassion in any time of trouble. 112</item>
               <item>32 A praier for grace not to be offended at the offences of the wicked. 115</item>
               <item>33 A praier against lying. 119</item>
               <item>34 A praier against Treason. page. 123</item>
               <item>35 A praier necessarie for this our time. 126</item>
               <item>36 Another. 131</item>
               <item>37 Another. 136</item>
               <item>38 A praier against heresie &amp; schisme. 139</item>
               <item>39 A praier for grace to carrie a true reuerence towardes Gods word. 142</item>
               <item>40 A praier for faire weather at any time as wel for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
<pb facs="tcp:176864:141"/>fruites to the earth, as for the receiuing of them and other blessings. 166</item>
               <item>41 Another praier after recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the fruites of the earth, with a complaint of the time. 170</item>
               <item>42 A thankesgiuing to God for the discouerie of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or faction whatsoeuer. page. 181</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:176864:142"/>
               <head>Peculiar prayers <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliable to particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> of sundrie states <hi>and degrees.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>1 A Praier for Parentes. page. 29</item>
               <item>2 A praier for a married man. page. 31</item>
               <item>3 A praier for a married wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. 33</item>
               <item>4 A praier for a woman great with childe. 37</item>
               <item>5 A praier for children. 39</item>
               <item>6 A praier for Schoolemaisters. page. 42</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:176864:142"/>
               <item>7 A praier for schollers. 44</item>
               <item>8 A praier for maisters of fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies. 46</item>
               <item>9 A praier for seruants. 48</item>
               <item>10 A praier for preachers. 62</item>
               <item>11 Another. 64</item>
               <item>12 A praier for the poore. page. 106</item>
               <item>13 A praier to God for them that are troubled in minde, page. 146</item>
               <item>14 Another. 151</item>
               <item>15 A praier for them that are visited with sickenesse. 153</item>
               <item>16 Another. 156</item>
               <item>17 A praier needfull for all the people of this land. 159</item>
               <item>18 A praier for her Maiestie. page. 163</item>
               <item>19 A special praier for her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties royall person, and
<pb facs="tcp:176864:143"/>the good estate of England. page. 174</item>
               <item>20 A briefe Narration of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uids case, with a briefe Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the same to the people of Englande, &amp;c. page. 187</item>
            </list>
            <closer>
               <hi>Glorie to God:</hi> AMEN.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:176864:143"/>
            <p>1601.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>OS HOMINI SVBLIME DEDIT</q>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Peter Short</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by Peter Short, dwelling on Bred-street hill at the signe of the Starre.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176864:144"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176864:144"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>